<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A iust and moderate answer to a most iniurious, and slaunderous pamphlet, intituled, An exact discouery of Romish doctrine in case of conspiracie and rebellion Wherein the innocency of Catholike religion is proued, and euery obiection returned vpon the Protestant accuser, and his owne profession. With licence of superior.</title>
            <author>Broughton, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112914</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848155</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848155</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13233</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07811)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13233)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1249:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A iust and moderate answer to a most iniurious, and slaunderous pamphlet, intituled, An exact discouery of Romish doctrine in case of conspiracie and rebellion Wherein the innocency of Catholike religion is proued, and euery obiection returned vpon the Protestant accuser, and his owne profession. With licence of superior.</title>
                  <author>Broughton, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the English secret press,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Richard Broughton.</note>
                  <note>A reply to the work by Thomas Morton.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  a²  B-P² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An answer to the supposed Discouery.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Morton, Thomas, 1564-1659. --  Exact discoverie of Romish doctrine in the case of conspiracie and rebellion, by pregnant observations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13233:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13233:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>A iust and moderate Anſwer</hi> To a moſt iniurious, and ſlaunderous Pamphlet, intituled, <hi>An exact Diſcouery of Romiſh doctrine in caſe of Conſpiracie and Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the innocency of Catholike religion is proued, and euery obiection returned vpon the Proteſtant Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, and his owne profeſſion.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Maltese cross</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 57. verſ. 1.</bibl>
               <p>Si veré vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Iuſtitiam loquimini: recta iudicate filij hominum.</p>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>With licence of Superior.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:13233:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13233:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT and mightie Prince, our gratious and dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, IAMES, by the grace of God, King of great Brittaine, France and Ireland, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the faith.</head>
            <p>TWo thinges (moſt Gratious Soueraigne) among the reſt of chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>feſt regard, in terrene and humane affaires, were euer appriſed at the higheſt value: Life, the preſent being: Fame and Reputation, the beautie and ſplendor theereof: The firſt giuing <hi>eſſe,</hi> aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>non eſſe,</hi> to the greateſt earthlie Creature, the other maintaining in ſome ſorte, a per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptuall life, and glorious liuing, when we be dead.</p>
            <p>Therefore, by how much the poſſeſſors of thoſe dignities, be more popular, publique, and greater in number, State, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſo many degrees, vnworthily and trecherouſlie to be depriued of them, is more iniurious, guil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie of wickedneſſe, and obnoxious to Reſtitution.</p>
            <p>Concerning the former; The late intended Conſpiracy againſt the life of your Royall Maieſtie, (the Life, Vnion, Rule, and Direction to theſe vnited Kingdomes) ſo many Nobles, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of eſteeme, was ſo heinous impiety, that nothing which is holy can make it Legitimate; no pretence of Religion can be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, to excuſe it: God and heauen condemne it, Men and earth deteſt it: Innocents bewaile it, the <hi>Nocent</hi> and vnhappie <hi>Delinquents</hi> themſelues, perceiuing how their Religion reproueth it, in repentance haue lamented it: Proteſtants exclaime againſt it, and your dutifull, Religious, and learned Catholikes, Prieſts, and others, which haue endured moſt for their profesſion, hold it in greateſt horror, and make it a ſubiect of their grieuous ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that any of their profesſion ſhould attempt ſo barbarous and vnnaturall cruelty, or practiſe any diſobedience at all to your Highneſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13233:3"/>
            <p> And will ſweare, proteſt, promiſe, and performe to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, whatſoeuer Loyaltie, Obedience, and dutie is due from a ſubiect to his Temporall Prince, by the word of God, lawe of Nature, or hath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne vſed by the ſubiects of this Kingdome, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny your P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogenito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Chriſtian, from the firſt to the laſt: acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and rend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to your honorable Counſaile, and all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in ciui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l cauſes, ſo much Honor, Reuerence and Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to all other Proteſtant ſubiects, like amitie and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourlie affection, as if they were of the ſame Religion, which we pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>feſſe.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſecond, of publike reproache, and defamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (moſt worthy Prince) if it only concerned the Catholikes of this Nation, although it be no eaſie queſtion to proue, that men in ſuch matters, and at ſuch times, are maſters of their fame: yet they could be content to burie it in their graue of obliuion with ſo many miſeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which they haue long ſuſteined, for their holy faith; and to ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Maledicimur et benedicimus, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem patimur et ſuſtinemu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, blaſphemamur et obſecramus:</hi> but when the <hi>Purgamenta huius mundi,</hi> and <hi>omnium peripſema,</hi> muſt be made the badge of all maintainers of that worſhippe, and all be ſtiled ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ditious and traiterous Perſons, quite contrarie to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe often Aſſertions, and publique Proclamations; That all Catholike ſubiects to all forraigne Princes, your Confederates, muſt weare that Liuerie, and their Soueraignes be attended with ſuch ſeruants; All Catholike ſchooles termed Seminaries of rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions: and ſo directly not only the reputations of all thoſe Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſities, Princes, and Prelates of the Church of God, but God himſelfe (whoſe howſe it is, and whoſe honor can neither be giuen nor taken away) is thus condemned: as is ſet forth in a late pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlett intituled, <hi>An exact Diſcouerie of Romiſh doctrine in caſe of Conſpiracie:</hi> Silence would be too ſuſpicious, of neglect in many greateſt duties, to God in heauen, his Church on earth, to your Maieſtie, and the whole Catholike world.</p>
            <p>Therefore I po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e wretch and ſinner an vnworthy member of that ſacred bodie of Chriſt, and one of your Highneſſe obedient ſubiects, in all ſubmiſsion craue pardon, not only to make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of Catholikes due and expected Loyaltie, to your Soueraigne Authoritie, and refute the friuoulous obiections of
<pb facs="tcp:13233:3"/> that Author: But with <hi>Dauid</hi> againſt <hi>Goliah</hi> in the behalfe of King <hi>Saul,</hi> and the people of God, to ſtrike with his owne ſword, and returne all and euery of his deadlie reaſons, vppon himſelfe, and his owne Profeſsion.</p>
            <p>Which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as I may lawfully obſerue, by common conſent of all, entreating of the law of conſcience, in this caſe, being onely to vſe our owne right of iuſt defence, and not to offend or defame Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, (which charitable expoſition, I deſire of all Proteſtant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:) So, if I had trauelled no farther into that doctrine, then to the laſt printed booke by your Maieſties Printer, of the late inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conſpiracy, I might as eaſily performe it: for that Proteſtant author giueth it out as a general Rule &amp; vndoubted Maxime, to all profeſſors of worſhip, to take armes, if their religion be in hazard: and that no priuate man could thinke his life more happily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, than to fight <hi>pro Aris:</hi> which is greater liberty, than any opinion which our aduerſarie can finde among Catholike Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo by him attached of treaſon and rebellion. But he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a more plaine and plentifull recitall, both of publike po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and practiſes, from all his neighbouring Allies in religion, to proue his owne profeſſion, to be both Seminary and Granary of ſuch prouiſion.</p>
            <p>Which I am more inforced vnto, becauſe this diſcouerer, by ſo many, not vſuall Catholike Authors, alleaged in his booke, diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his inueterate malice againſt vs, that he was now in his deſired oppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tunitie, deliuered with ioy of that, wherewith hee had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed ſo long in paine: or to renew in ſubtile m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nner, his old good affection to your Maieſtie, doth marſhall you euen now, (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all his re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſons be too childiſh) in the number of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uell Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, Excommunicates, Apoſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, and the infamous of all ages, not only Princes, but baſe perſons. So that eyther for diſloyalty to your Highneſſe, or inured inflamed hatred vnto vs, or both, hee can ſinde no cent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of his ſlaunders, except your Maieſtie bee m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de the man and marke, where at the pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll canons and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of holy Church, did point and leuell hundreds of yeares, bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re you were borne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r his relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on receiued life.</p>
            <p>This is the miſerable &amp; diſtreſſed ſtate, of many thouſands your moſt loyall and louing ſubiects, (dread Liege) for their faithfull dutie to God, and a religion taught in this kingdome, and imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:13233:4"/> by all your progenitors, and our anceſtors, ſo many hundred yeares, from their firſt conuerſion: that euery aduerſary may preach, and print againſt vs, and make their challenges; as though eyther for ignorance we could not, or for diſtruſt of our cauſe, we were vnwilling to make them anſwer, or come to triall: when quite contrary, wee haue, often, earneſtly, and by all meanes wee could, deſired to haue it graunted, with equall conditions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt ſelected and beſt learned Doctors of that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>And at this preſent, when your cheefeſt Proteſtant Cleargie, (Biſhops, and others) is aſſembled, wee moſt humbly intreat, this ſo reaſonable a <hi>Placet;</hi> that although they will not (as we feare) ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily conſent to an indifferent choyce, oppoſition, and defence in queſtions; yet, at the leaſt, (to auoide the wonder of the world) they will be content, that we may haue publike audience, for thoſe articles, opinions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and practiſe, for which we are ſo much condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and perſecuted. If wee ſhall not be able to defend or proue, any poſition generally maintained in our doctrine, to be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to thoſe rules in diuinity, which your Maieſty, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant lawes of <hi>England</hi> (we can offer no more) haue confirmed for holy, the canonicall Scriptures, the firſt generall Councells, the daies of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and the Primatiue Church; let the penalties be impoſed and executed againſt vs. If we performe it, or this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition may not be admitted, we truſt, that both our office to God, and duty to Prince, is diſcharged in this point.</p>
            <p>Your royall Perſon, and that honorable conſiſtory now aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, or hold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in your doctrine, to be the ſupreame ſentencer, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in ſpirituall buſineſſe in this kingdome: wee therefore hope you will not (in a Court from whence no appeale is allowed, and in matters of ſuch conſequence) proceede to iudgement, or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of execution, before the arraigned is ſommoned to anſwer, hath receiued, or refuſed triall, is, or can be proued guilty: for it is a Sages ſentence: <hi>Iudicem &amp; Aram eſſe idem;</hi> euen in ordinary<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. Rhetor.</note> Iudges: becauſe people iniured or diſtreſſed flie to them both for refuge. And we humbly craue licence to ſay vnto you, as <hi>Liberius,</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> anſwered <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Emperour, perſwading<note place="margin">Theodor. dialog. hiſt. trip, l, 5. c. 17</note> him to ſubſcribe to the baniſhement of ſaint <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> the great Gretian Patriarke, <hi>O Imperator, Iudicia eccleſiaſtica decet tam max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ima</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:4"/> 
               <hi>proferri iuſtitia.</hi> If we be condemned, &amp; our cauſe be iuſt, and religion true, it is God, and not man, againſt whom you proceede in ſentence: if our profeſſion be erroneous, and yet for conſent with ſo many Nations, and ſo long continuance, it is left vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; you onely pardon the frailty and ignorance of earthly men, and fight not with the heauenly.</p>
            <p>Deny not that to vs, your euer true and obedient ſubiects, in a religion ſo antient, which your colleged Princes, the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and Arch-duke, doe offer to the ſo many yeares diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Netherlanders, vpon their temporall ſubmittance, in ſo late an imbraced doctrine. That which the Arrian Emperors of the Eaſt, permitted to the Catholikes, (Biſhops, Prieſts, Churches, tolleration:) what the barbarian Vandalls often offered, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times truly performed in <hi>Africke;</hi> what the Turkiſh Emperor in <hi>Greece,</hi> and Proteſtant Princes in <hi>Germany,</hi> and other places allow to them of our religion, can be no ſingular offence, to grant vnto vs once in ſo many yeares, though our religion were vntrue. It would be acceptable to all Catholike Princes, conformable to the examples of proteſtant Rulers, not vnaunſwerable to your owne princelie pietie, pittie and promiſe, no diſguſt to any equally minded Proteſtant, or Puritane at home, a Iubily to vs diſtreſſed; and (to anſwer all the diſcouerers quarrells in one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence) a warrant of ſecurity to your Maieſty, in all opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe terrors and dangers which he conceiteth: from which, and all others, of what kinde ſoeuer, we moſt humbly beſeech the infinite Maieſty of God, to preſerue your Highneſſe, and ſend you, your Queene, and poſteritie, all happineſſe and felicity in heauen and earth.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13233:5"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13233:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A generall Cenſure of this ſlanderous Pamphlet; proouing, that no one Argument therein can conclude the Authors Intent.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Diſcouerer</hi> of Terrors and Daungers neuer before ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, like vnto the eſpiall of King <hi>Alexander,</hi> which either<note place="margin">Qu. Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. in vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Alexand.</note> hauing his phantaſie and interior powers diſtempered, or his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſences out of order, or both farre from frameing right ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and true judgement, brought worde to his wiſe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Emperor, that an army of enemies was approaching to aſſault him, when they were but a ſmall company of ſilie Apes, imitating ſouldiers with a march on the Mountaynes, doubteth not to call ſuch his deluded viſion, <hi>An exact Diſcouery of Romiſh Doctrine in the caſe of Conſpiracie and Rebellion:</hi> and a little after, <hi>A Plaine Diſcouery of the Rebellious Doctrine of the Romiſh Church;</hi> and termeth <hi>Romiſh Schooles</hi> (to vſe his owne wordes) <hi>Seminaries of Rebellions,</hi> and telleth vs, <hi>Popiſh Prieſts, as alſo their Adherents, be worthily executed for ſeditious and trayterous perſons.</hi> Hitherto is the ſtrange Diſcriall of this great Diſcouerer, not as yet yeelding any Reaſon, but that we may thinke his braine diſtempered, conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Apes, for mortall Enemies, their ſtickes and Reeds for dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounding weapons. Therefore ſuppoſing, for his Reports of ſo vnprobable things, he ſhould be deluded as a man illuded, and ſtrangely miſ-taken, except he pretended ſome ſtrange and vn-v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall Argument, for his rare Intelligence, falling into a ſecond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamitie, like a farre Trauailer, giueth foorth, that theſe wonders be collected out of the expreſse <hi>Dogmaticall Principles, of Popiſh Prieſts and Doctors, and from their Publike Poſitions and Practiſes,</hi> and accordingly entituleth euery leafe, <hi>Romiſh Poſitions and Practiſes of Rebellion.</hi> What ſimply meaning minde would not be amazed with ſuch a meſſage, eſpecially when hee profeſſeth theſe things to be collected, <hi>not without direction from Superiors.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:6"/>
               <p> But, to ouerthrowe his laſt Aſsertion; firſt, There is neyther name of Author (the Current of time ſtreaming for him) to the Pamphlet, nor Licence and Priuilege of Impreſſion, as all Books publiſhed by Authoritie by Engliſh Proteſtants ought to haue: And therefore to be accompted a Libell.</p>
               <p>Touching the other, of proouing his Intent by our owne <hi>Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Principles, and Publique Poſitions,</hi> it is ſo impudent an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueth, That if all his falſely applied Authorities were to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for Goſpel, yet not one ſuch <hi>Dogmaticall</hi> and <hi>Publike Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>Practiſe,</hi> to the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſgrace of our holy Religion, and to rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his ſlaunderous accuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, is regiſtred in his whole <hi>Diſcouery,</hi> Except this Accuſer will accuſe and conuict himſelfe of treaſon, both with God and man, to endite his Maieſty our gratious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine<note place="margin">Rat. 1. pag. 1. 2. 3. 4 5. &amp; rat. 2. 3.</note> of higheſt diſobedience to his King &amp; Creator in heauen, engroſsing him in the Catologue of cenſured, excommunicate, and denounced Hereticks, Apoſtataes, Tirants, and Vſurpers: which if he intendeth to doe, at his firſt entrance he hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a crime <hi>Laeſae Maiestatis</hi> if the lawe of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> be not dead<note place="margin">Statut. 13. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. 1.</note> with her ſelfe. If he will not be expounded in ſuch ſence, and to place all the honorable and inferior Magiſtrates, and Proteſtants alſo not in Authority, in that order, proportion of degrees obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued (a paradoxe moſt monſtrous, and not to bee imagined by any learned Catholike) he warreth not againſt the Roman church, and ſchooles, his aymed obiect; but againſt poetically or childiſhlie feigned <hi>Proſopopeis,</hi> and <hi>Chimeres</hi> of his owne creation; for againſt only ſuch his Arguments haue their force, againſt ſuch as we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme them, they are too fooliſh.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to giue life to his feeble or dead obiections, we muſt<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 1. pag. 1. 2, 3. 4 5. 6. 7.</note> condiſcend at his high will and pleaſure, not only that all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of England are formall heretickes, ſentenced againſt, and cenſured, (all which we abſolutely denie:) But that all penall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees in the Canon and Papall lawe cited in his Treatiſe, are due and belonging vnto them, which the whole Chriſtian world will witneſſe againſt: And that in no Kingdome where Proteſtants be planted, England, Scotland, Ireland, Fraunce, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eland, Heluetia, Lorraine, Denmar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, any part of Germanie, Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, Poland or any other they be practized as in force<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or put in execution.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:6"/>
               <p> Thirdly, we muſt giue conſent (againſt all Catholike ſchooles)<note place="margin">Rat. 2. pag. 9. 10. 11.</note> that there is no difference betweene the chief ſpirituall power and preeminence which we giue to Popes, and mere ciuill ſoueraine Authority ouer Princes, and all temporall things, when we only attribute the firſt, and not the ſecond to the Roman See.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, we muſt not denie to this <hi>Diſcouerer,</hi> but if the Pope<note place="margin">Rat. 4. pag 14. 15 16. 17. 18 19. 22 23. 24. 25, &amp;c.</note> commandeth Armes againſt our Prince (a metaphiſicall &amp; need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe feare to be put in practiſe) we would formally be conformed to ſuch precept: yet when we giue a true, reall, preſent, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall inſtance, that the ſame Papall Authoritie now commandeth all Catholicks to performe all dutifull loyaltie and obedience to his Majeſtie, (more then the proteſtant Cleargie of England can ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie for themſelues) and <hi>quia Papa ſiciubet, et prohibet</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: it will be no ſatisfaction for good behauiour to this obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. Theſe and more ſuch abſurdities muſt be yeelded vnto, if any one of his Arguments is to be reſpected. But I muſt needs<note place="margin">All Proteſtants agree in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a contrary Religion.</note> put him in minde, that he hath behelde his viſage too much in the glaſſe of <hi>Wickliffe, Huſſe, Waldo, Luther, Munſter, Swinglius, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, Beza, Knoxe, Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Sands, Rogesr,</hi> and all Proteſtants of all places, (as I will demonſtrate hereafter) how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they varied in other queſtions, yet all jumping togither in this, that Kinges and Magiſtrates of a different Religion, are not to be obeyed, but contemned, contradicted, depoſed, and not worthy to be accounted eyther Princes or men: And this colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, bloudie, and ſtained ſpectacle or <hi>ſpeculum,</hi> hath ſo deluded his eyes, that he can ſee nothing but rebellions, ſeditions, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience in profeſſors of Religion, though neuer ſo holy and approued. But as we d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffer from him &amp; his adherents, in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chiefeſt articles of Religion; ſo we vtterlie renounce both their doctrine and practiſe in this poynt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The first Reaſon againſt Catholiques confuted, and returned vpon Protestaats.</hi> CHAP.. II.</head>
               <p>I Will come to his particular Reaſons: The firſt whereupon (as a moſt certaine ground and foundation, hee frameth the
<pb facs="tcp:13233:7"/> reſt of his building) is regiſtred in theſe wordes. <hi>Their generall Aſsumption wherevpon all their rebellious Poſitious are founded, is this; that all</hi> Proteſtants <hi>are hereticks, and excommunicate.</hi> Whereby it appeareth by his owne judiciall decree, that if Catholicks doe not teach, <hi>that all</hi> Proteſtants <hi>are hereticks and excomunicate,</hi> that then no poſitions which we maintaine, are rebellious, becauſe he telleth vs all ſuch are builded vpon that <hi>Aſſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore to purge vs of all theſe crimes, by the firſt ſentence of this Accuſer; I anſwere, this poſition <hi>(all Proteſtants are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and excommunicate)</hi> is neyther a generall <hi>Aſſumption</hi> in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion, neither doe I ſuppoſe that any one particular learned Catholicke in this kingdome (yet ſuch can beſt judge of their country caſe) doth or will defend this opinion, which he calleth our generall <hi>Aſſumpsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For firſt, there is not at this preſent one Proteſtant abſolutelie (then not all Proteſtantes) eſteemed with vs to be in that ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, within the Dominions of our Soueraigne, of what condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer to my knowledge: neyther is there daunger thereof hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, except ſuch wicked and ſlaunderous writinges (as this <hi>Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerie)</hi> be made incitemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and citations for ſuch cenſures. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many, or moſt of the opinions defended by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of England were condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d for hereſies, both in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue and later dayes of the Church of Chriſt, in <hi>Iouinian, Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius, Aerius, Berengarius, Waldo, Wickliffe, Huſſe,</hi> and others: yet it doth not preſently followe, that all which imitate thoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines ſhould be termed Hereticks, as the firſt obſtinate Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and pertinatious defendors of thoſe nouelties were. For according to the ſentence of S. <hi>Thomas, Halenſis, Silueſter, Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D. Th. 2. 2. q. 11. ar. 2. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll 1. p. q. 181. m. 1. §. 1. Durand. 4. diſt. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 5. art. 6 Syl. v. Haereſ. n. 5. Auguſt. l. de vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. Cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip.</note> and the common opinion of Schooles, ignorance (euen vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible) excuſeth from hereſie. And this is the doctrine of S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> who in his booke <hi>de vtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tate credendi</hi> writeth thus, <hi>He is an Hereticke who for temporall Commodity, or Vayne-glory, or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallitie, eyther begetteth or followeth falſe Opinyon, but he who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth Hereticks</hi> (the caſe of the major part of english Proteſtants) <hi>is a man illuded with a certayne Imagination of pyetie and truth.</hi> And he affirmeth, that the firſt (wherof I hope England is not ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull) is an Hereticke, and not the other. And againſt the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts he telleth vs, tbat he which holdeth that of Chriſt which <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13233:7"/> the hereticke did, thinking it to be the Catholike faith (as<note place="margin">Auguſt. l. 4 c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Donauſt. c. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> hundreds of thouſands of ignorantly ſeduced Proteſtants doe, which heare no other doctrine but miniſters Sermons) is not yet an Hereticke, except when the truth of the Catholike doctrine is made manifeſt, he will reſiſt it. And Cardin all <hi>Allane</hi> himſelfe<note place="margin">Cardin. Al lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſo often obiected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his <hi>diſcouery,</hi> thus writeth of that holy father and this queſtion. <hi>Beatus Auguſtinus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>monuit, decipi ab Haereticus quis di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itur, &amp; Haeretu is credere, nec tamen propriè eſt Haereticus.</hi> He is not properly an Hereticke, which is deceaued of Hereticks, and beleeueth Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cks.</p>
               <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>condly, by common conſent of Catholike Doctors, both<note place="margin">Adrian, quandl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. art, 1. Sylu. v. Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ q. 2. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 4 diſt. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. q. 2. Alph. de Caſt. Io. de tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. Clement. 1. ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. Ioh. 22. Bull. Martin. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etit. 1000 miniſ Anſw of Oxford by Adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nit. 1 &amp; 2. parliam. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. W. &amp;c.</note> ſufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nowl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge of the truth propoſed, and obſtinate perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie in not emb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ceing it, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ſuch defence of the contrary, is required to Hereſie: in which caſe the principall preachers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in England, which haue ſo often chaunged their opinions, and didde volun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ily ſubmitte thei. Religion (both P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in their millinary Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, and the Vniuerſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Proteſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts in their Anſwere) to his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieſtie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, to be chaunged or continued and in eſſentiall point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſarie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ation as the Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tanes haue oft written, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e them to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t all, (true faith cannot be ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nged corrected) then to be obſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addicted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o their profeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</p>
               <p>Thirdly many defend that although a man deſireth to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th and ſo profeſſeth hereſy in ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rance, (though he ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſuch caſe) yet he is not to be accounted an Hereticke.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, that a man dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> in his f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h (<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> l. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. de loc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 4.</note> common and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts) is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an Heret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, all Here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes (as inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nall) be not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>biect to Cenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and Exco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, no comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion is f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biden<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> with any, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> obi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h from <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitanus,</hi> that where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is noto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vs. Hereſie 1.) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not any decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Excommuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ion: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> abſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tely ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> general <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be both ſo cenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13233:8"/> which, conſenteth <hi>Cunerns, Nauarre,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, alſo after ſuch proceedings, (except ſpecially excepted)<note place="margin">Concil. Conſt. Suares de Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. gloſs. c. Cum deſideras de ſent. excommun.</note> the caſe of wife, children, ſeruants &amp;c. bringeth exemption.</p>
               <p>Seauenthly, no Proteſtant, or hereticke, or Archehereticke, not excommunicate by name (as none in England is) lyeth ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to any penalty pretended.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect </seg>
                  </label> But it will be obiected, from the ſecond Reaſon, that Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes holde the Pope head of the Church, to haue a ciuill power alſo ouer Kings, and <hi>circa omnia temporalia;</hi> therfore he may both depoſe Princes, and commaund ſubiectes to arme againſt them, once excommunicate.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, I aunſwere concerning Prieſts, moſt maligned in this matter, that the canon Lawe itſelfe is to the contrary, where be theſe words; <hi>De Epiſcopis vero vel quibuſlibet Clericis quod nec ſua</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Decret 2 pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. cauſ. 23. q. 8. De epiſcopis, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>authoritate, nec authoritate, Romani pontific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> arma accipere valeant, facile probatur.</hi> Neyther Biſhops nor any Clerks may take armes either by their owne authority, or the authority of the Pope of Rome. And reaſons be added there, authorized by <hi>Gregory</hi> 13. alleadged here againſt vs in this Treatiſe. Therefore all of that order be abſolutely freed from that ielouſie, and may anſwer with<note place="margin">Ambroſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> orat. contra Auxent.</note> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> againſt <hi>Auxentius. Quid ergo turbamini, volens nunquam ius deſeram: coactus re pugnare non noui potero dolere, poero flere, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero gemere, aduerſus arma, milites, Gothos quoque, lacrimae meae, mea armaſunt, talia enim ſunt manimenta Sacer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otis, aliter nec de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, nec poſſum reſiſtere. Therefore why are you troubled, willingly I neuer will forſake right, compelled I know not to reſiſt, I may be ſorie, I may weepe, I may groane againſt Armes, ſould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers and the Gothes alſo, my teares are my armour, for ſuch are the defence of Prieſts, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I neyther ought, nor can reſiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, I aunſwere, if any man holde that opinion, of ſuch a power ouer Princes in Popes, yet they will plead, it is more tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable to defend ſuch authority in one ſupreame Paſtor and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gouernor in the Church, whereof Princes be ſheepe, and not ſheepeheardes (as the late wiſe Lord Treaſurer acknowledged of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that ſhee was <hi>Ouis,</hi> and not <hi>Paſtor)</hi> then to committe the cenſuring of Princes caſes, to ſuch ſeditious iudges, and ſuperiors, as Proteſtant both publique poſitions and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes aſsigne; by which, not only euery <hi>Wickliffe, Luther, Caluine,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13233:8"/> 
                  <hi>Cranmer, Knoxe,</hi> and ſuch ſupreame men, but the artizans and baſeſt people in euery Elderſhippe, may ſitte in iudgement vpon their Soueraigne, Cite, Excomunicate and Depoſe him, euen for ordinarie offences, as themſelues expound conuenient for their owne aduantage, as I will alleadge from their publique opinions hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> And if this man will inſtance that the Author of the booke <hi>De iuſta abdicat. Henric.</hi> 3. teacheth and <hi>excomuni conſenſu,</hi> that it is lawfull for a priuate man to kill a Tyrant. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwere, it is more then diſobedience, for any ſubiect in England to make ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with his mercifull Prince: And yet whatſoeuer that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Author writeth, or this Diſputer citeth from him, that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is not the common conſent; but againſt, not only the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<note place="margin">Alphonſ. Caſtr. contr. Haereſ. v. tyrannus. Petrus Gregorius in fine 2. to. de Republ. Cune<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e offic. priecip. chriſtian. Hentic. quodl. 6. q. 23. Turrec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l. 2. c. 113. Couo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Victor de poteſt. eccl. concil. 1. q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Palat. 4 D. 25. Turrect. l. 1. c. 87.</note> conſent of Catholike authors, <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtro, Petrus, Gregorius, Cunerus</hi> and others, but againſt the generall councell of Conſtance it ſelfe, to which, all Catholikes muſt conform them ſelues.</p>
               <p>Secondlie, I anſwere for all Catholickes in generall, to the maine Obiection, that <hi>Henricus, Victor, Iohannes de Turrecr, Couoruuius</hi> and the common opinion of Schooles doe teach, that there is no ſuch mere Temporall and Regall power in Popes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Princes, and ciuill affaires; but a Supreame ſpirituall, as that is which they clayme in Temporalls <hi>in ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> and is not (to vſe this Diſputers words) <hi>Aciuill power Soueraigne ouer Kings directly;</hi> but only a ſpirituall preeminence (the ſubiect, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, office and end thereof being ſuch) for the ſpirituall good and behoofe of the church of Chriſt, committed to his Vicar and chiefe Delegate here on earth, by commiſſion of feeding, gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ruling, binding, looſing, ſhutting, opening, and the like in holy Scripture, and authoritatiuely citeing, ſummoning, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing and cenſuring both ſheepe and other ſheepeheards of our Sauiours flocke.</p>
               <p>Yet thirdly I anſwere, that the defendors of this ſentence doe farther teach, that this iuriſdiction and power againſt ſheepe or inferior ſheepeheards; is not to be put in practiſe, but in caſes of obſtinacie, contempt, and incorrigibilitie in the offendor, and being onely for the profite and vtilitie of the Spouſe of Chriſt, &amp; his myſticall body, it may not be exerciſed where greater loſſe, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,
<pb facs="tcp:13233:9"/> and hazard, then good and profite is to enſue from thence. The cauſe muſt be iuſt, the ſuggeſtion not vntrue, the meanes not turbulent tending to deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the maintainers of this doctrine doe not vrge greater indignitie, or defend any ſentence more offenſiue (in equallinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to any prelate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſheepe, or ſheepheard, then to the chiefeſt ſheepehea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d vnder Chriſt, the Pope him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe: for they all with one conſent affirme, that in caſe of hereſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (now in queſtion) hee<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. v. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2. §. 4. palud ib. &amp; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Turrecr. li. 2 ſum. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l 4 c. 18. Aug. de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l. de iuſt. haeret. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. 12 q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tic. 2. Can. l. 4 de loc. c. vlt. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dub. l b. quaeſtion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r q. 11.</note> is eyther actually and really depoſed, or to be depoſed. The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts doe holde he is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> depoſed, if hee fall into her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſie; with whome <hi>Io de Turrecrem. Augustin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s de Ancona, Castro,</hi> and other Diuines conſent, which C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſure <hi>Wickcl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffe</hi> and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſors did imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e vppon P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and temporall Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, eyther for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rime. Others, as <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anus,</hi> and <hi>Cordubenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> affir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be depoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, And ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the diſcipline of the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch of God. that theſe men, and all Catho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les (euen in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe) as confid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtions, for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w and when, and by<note place="margin">Panormita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ſup. ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Significa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i. Canoniſt in c. Si P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> whom Popes may be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſed, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſpeake or write of the greateſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edges of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Apoſtolike See. And <hi>Panormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> a Canoniſt, with others, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo confident in this buſineſſe, that they teach, a Pope may be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſed for any ſinne, that is ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch of Chriſt, if he be inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rigible.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, the preſent Profeſſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which handle this q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Popes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inces, doe not holde any ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r opinion tending to the indignitie or dommage of any Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teſtant Regent, more than to all oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs in equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll termes; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> what is now by them main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ained, was publike d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctrine befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Proteſtancie had either pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce or pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>brace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and at t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e do iuſtifie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he like ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncerning all Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Rulers, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all ballaunce of comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat openly w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thout <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>proofe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ons.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, to giue contentment to all that will not be contentious, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct to be ſingular in perſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing or domag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Church of God. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Authors doe not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>olutely ſubiect to the Papall and Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuall au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, but in caſe of iniuries offered, or great imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>diment of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> good, more preeminent then the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mporall. And in ſuch c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:13233:9"/> euen in temporall affaires, and among ſuch powers and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, iniuries offered, and iuſt right denied, or hindered, giueth a prerogatiue to equalles <hi>iure belli,</hi> among Kings and ciuill Regents, to recouer their owne, redeeme their wrong, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>equite their iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, where the offendor denieth to make requitall.</p>
               <p>Therefore, ſeeing this <hi>Diſcouerer</hi> cannot finde anie ſuch ciuil power ſoueraigne ouer Kinges challenged by Popes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which hee ſo much inueigheth, nor any other more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly intended againſt Proteſtant Princes, then all others in like proceedings; let him draw his weapon againſt thoſe by whome he is aſſaulted in this kind. Firſt againſt the Canoniſts and the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſts euen in England, and of the Arches, except they will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the more receaued opinion of like prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſors: ſecondly againſt himſelfe &amp; all Proteſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt write <hi>s.</hi> Againſt the firſt, bicauſe (which is his caſe in queſtion) they defend that the empror is lord of all the world, inſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch that <hi>Bartholus</hi> the great Leg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affirmes,<note place="margin">Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thol. in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag. ad rep. imen. gloſſe per vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab. Qui filii, &amp;c.</note> that peraduenture it is h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſie to te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch the contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſaith he) it is againſt the ſcripture, <hi>Exiſt ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctum à Caeſare v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is,</hi> where the whole wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld and Princes thereof were at his deſignement: And (which the Proteſtants alleadge for tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Princes ſupremacie) <hi>omnis anima poteſtatibus ſublimiorjbus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita ſit:</hi> therefore (as he reaſoneth) all Princes be ſubiect to him, as the higheſt power. And in this caſe of Armes and death (which this man ſo often obiecteth) the cauſe is more daungerous in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, that in the whole papall and canon law of the Popes, there is no penaltie of death againſt any hereticke, or excommunicate, neyther is ſuch punniſhement to bee inflicted by any ſpirituall Iudge, or executioner: But that kinde of reuenge or juſtice, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Codic. haeret. leg. Adrian et Cod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. de Iudaeis leg. Quicunque.</note> prouided by the emperiall and ciuill Conſtitutions, and by temporall Authority and <hi>brach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um ſcecuiare</hi> to be put in practiſe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, lett him battaile againſt himſelfe, and his Proteſtant<note place="margin">Proteſtants Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of all others is the greateſt e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to Princes and Catholique worſhip the moſt fauourable.</note> brethren, which of all people in the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lde, that euer were, or be, are the moſt guilty in theſe proceedings, as I will at large demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate hereafter) and Catholikes of all moſt innocent. For ſeeing all profeſſors of Religion, Iſraelites, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gans, Catholikes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and all others euer preſcribed ſome meanes and manner to keepe both Rulers and the ruled in order: of all people to whom that authority was attributed by any. The Popes of Rome
<pb facs="tcp:13233:10"/> (proportion of time and place couſidered) haue beene the actors of the feweſt tranſlations of titles in Princes. Not aboue foure or fiue examples can be giuen in the whole chriſtian worlde in aboue 1500 yeares, and not many excommunications from the firſt of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hillip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Emperour (as ſome ſuppoſe by the<note place="margin">Euſch hiſtor.</note> Pope of Rome) or of <hi>Archad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> by Pope <hi>Innoc n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> the firſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 400 yeares after Chriſt; when the Prophettes and Prieſts of<note place="margin">Nice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hor. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. in Arc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad.</note> Iurie depoſed more in one Kingdome; and the exceſſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans is not to be recited. And the Proteſtants themſelues ſince their originall haue depoſed as many or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n all the Popes in to many yeares, and that onelie for Religion, when for that qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll not one Prince in the Popedome hath loſt his Diademe, nor any without common conſent of the Chriſtian worlde. For Proteſtants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I inſtance in the Prince of Geneua depoſed; and in the King of Spaine, and the preſent Arche-duke in the Lowe Countries, expelled from their Right, the Kinge of Polonia in Sweueland at this preſent in litle better eſtate, the Queene Regent in Scotland ſo made a ſubiect, and his Maieſties mother depoſed, the Emperour denied his allowance of tribute for the Turkiſhe warres, his Townes taken, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ept againſt him, the Duke of Loraine, and others in the like predicament.</p>
               <p>And the violent attempts which they haue vndertaken, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt their Princes, for this quarrell of Religion, haue beene more, then all excommunications of Princes by Popes, for any reſpect what<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er; the particulars will appeare in their proper place.</p>
               <p>And whence can all theſe impious practiſes proceed, with ſo gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, but from their moſt impious and rebellious publiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poſition? you haue heard before, that the proces of Popes is ſuch in this buſines that no Prince (except more wicked th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n any now liuing, or as vnfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tunate as ſome foure or fiue in all the time of Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty in the worlde) neede ſtand in daunger.</p>
               <p>Contrariewiſe, by Proteſtant religion, no ſinner, or no King:<note place="margin">Conſt. Concil. in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Wickcl. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>. to. 6. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Luth. Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in in Dan. Suingl lib. 4. Philipp. Nichol. fund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. Caluin. Sect &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Luther</hi> denieth all obedience to Princes differing from him in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; calling them Pilates, Tyrants, Herods, Iudas, and that his Proteſtants handes muſt be imbrued with bloud in ſuch caſes. <hi>Caluin</hi> telleth, that <hi>ipſo facto</hi> they are bereaued. If no permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Swinglius</hi> doctrine, no Prince with him, and all bee Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs
<pb facs="tcp:13233:10"/> that be ſlaine in rebellion for that quarrell. The engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant<note place="margin">Confer. 14. 1604 pag. 47. Luther. lib. capt. Babyl.</note> Notes (as his Maieſtie is witne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) vppon the Bible doe not diſalowe the killing of a Prince in ſuch caſes. And this is to bee perfect Proteſtant diſciples of their Apoſtle <hi>Luther,</hi> who taught, no lawe can be impoſed vpon Chriſtians, but as they will, all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane lawes muſt be taken away. Therefore ſaieth <hi>Caluin, Beza,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tr ordin. Burg. in Reman ſup. edict. Reg. Gall, Petr. Frar, or<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contr. Sect. Defen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Reg. &amp; Relig.</note> 
                  <hi>Athomannus, Spiphazius,</hi> and the reſt of that holie Sinode, that Kinges, Queenes, their children, and poſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritie (l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Kinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe againe) and all Magiſtrates muſt be put to death, and ſo euery particular Proteſtant muſt be more then a Pope, an Emperour, or rather a god, to put Princes to death at their pleaſute: and we muſt ſay with the Conſiſtorian Proteſtants, not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerie pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man may be executioner of Princes: but teach, that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie to aſſigne rewardes for ſuch murtherers of Rulers; wee muſt not call them Kings or Superiours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but Tirants, Monſters, and not worthy of life. But more of this hereafter, in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall poſitions and practiſes.</p>
               <p>The reſt of the penal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies which this Author alleadgeth as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing<note place="margin">Catholikes denie no temporall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> duety to Proteſtants.</note> to the excommunicate, and ſuch heretickes, and which he writeth, that Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olikes doe teach, are due, and to be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon all Proteſtants of England, be thus recited: to ſpoile Proteſtants of their goods; deny t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thes to the Miniſters; not pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing debts to Creditors; ſeruants not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full to Maſters; wiues not beneuolent to Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bands; Pare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts diſ-inhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iting Children; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren not obeying P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rents; kinſmen to kindred, and countriemen to their Countrie to be vnkinde. But I haue anſwered before, that theſe ſocieties are not to be denied to the Proteſtants of England, becauſe we doe not eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eme them in that caſe of heretickes, and excommunicates. Secondly the world is witnes for vs, and againſt this Obiector, that we as truly and ſincerely performe theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications and reſpects to our country proteſtants, as they them ſelues, and rather in more ample manner. And although Tithes be due to ſpirituall Miniſters, for Sacraments and holie thinges, which we doe not receaue from them, yet we doe not withdrawe<note place="margin">Concil. Conſt. in artic. Wickcliff.</note> their payment to the proteſtant Cleargie, neither ſay as their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir <hi>Wickliffe</hi> did; that they be but almes, and may be taken awaie at princes pleaſures. Thirdly I anſwere, that thoſe canonicall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments he citeth againſt the cenſured, were not of purpoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daind
<pb facs="tcp:13233:11"/> againſt his proteſtancy; but the decrees of ſuch proceedings may be great-grandfather to that Religion: not now in vſe either in this kingdome, France, Heluetia, Sweueland, Denmarke, and moſt part of Germany, or in farther circuit. And if the penal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the generall Councell of Trent repreſenting Pope, Prelates, Princes, and the whole church of Chriſt, are not yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fourty yeares continuance receaued in the recited Prouinces, or Kingedomes: There is not ſo great daunger, that thoſe Papall paines will euer giue to this man ſo much cauſe of ſo outragious exclamations. They were long before the birth of proteſtancie, prouided for countries and people whence hereſies had not ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not where ſuch opinions haue preeminence. And if it ſhould pleaſe his Maieſtie to reſtore the Catholike faith in England, yet there is not perill that proteſtants ſhould fall to ſuch feares of theſe penall conſtitutions to be admitted: penalties are not ſo ſoone impoſed, their nature is to be reſtricted and not dilated. If ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other kingdomes vnder Catholike Regents, Fraunce, Sweue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Bohemia, Polonia, Tranſiluania &amp;c. doe not conſent to their admittance: This Iland one of the laſt by cituation, and ſo long at variaunce with the Roman Church, is not likelie to be the firſt in that, wherein nature deſireth to be the laſt. We haue not now an other Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> Inheretrix to the Crowne, to be joyned in mariadge with a potent Prince, in whoſe Dominions they be in force; ſimbolizing with husband, conformity in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie diſcipline is neuer like to breed you ſcruples in this behalfe. And yet in ſuch a metaphiſicall caſe <hi>(nemo laeditur niſi à ſeipſo)</hi> though you haue anowed to be an heretike and excommunicate, you muſt be cited, and admoniſhed before cenſure, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate before and after, or elſe your daunger is not deadlie.</p>
               <p>Thus I haue proued at lardge, as my violent and diſtreſſed leaſure would giue me allowance, that the chiefeſt building of all theſe ſlaunders againſt vs, is ruinate and ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rthrowne; that we doe not eſteeme all Proteſtants for heretickes and excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, as he pretendeth: neither that they are ſubiect to ſuch pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, as he alleadgeth; that they are not cenſured, or as ſuch to be depriued of any ciuill ſocietie, communication, their goodes, liues, liberties, dignities, honor, homage, fealtie, ſubiection, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, loue, or any thing pretious, their proper and peculiar; but
<pb facs="tcp:13233:11"/> contrariewiſe to enioy and poſſeſſe thoſe priueledges, in as ample manner and freedome, as if they were of the ſame Religion which we defend.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer to the firſt Reaſon.</label> Now I will with breuitie anſwere to his particular pretended reaſons, grounded vpon the generall before confuted: And firſt to his firſt <hi>Sillogiſme,</hi> or rather <hi>Sophiſme;</hi> the maior propoſition whereof is already ouerthrowne, and only requiring repetition, is as followeth: <hi>They who by their ſlaunderous doctrine make all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants (in their common cenſure heretickes) ſo odious and unworthy of any ciuill or naturall ſociety, muſt neceſſarily be adiudged ſeditious, and intollerable among the Proteſtants:</hi> My anſwere is abſolute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that no learned Catholike ſo reputeth the Proteſtants, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one Proteſtant of this kingdome; but attributeth (or ought ſo to do by his Religion) as much terrene honor, homage, duty and loue to our King, his honorable Counſaile, and all in Authority in their degrees, and vnfeined affection to the reſt, as if they were of the ſame faith and profeſſion in Religion.</p>
               <p>Then the minor propoſition (if the ſame <hi>medium</hi> be kept) muſt needs be falſe, which is this: <hi>But the Romiſh Seminaries and Ieſuites doe brand all Proteſtants with deteſtable crimes; thereby to deny them all ciuill and naturall Reſpects. Ergo.</hi> I anſwer, If the firſt part of this ſecond propoſition, be vnderſtood of the wickedneſſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Engliſh Proteſtants, not only condemned of their brethren<note place="margin">Admonit. 1. &amp; 2. Parliam. perit. 1000. Miniſt. Cartw. againſt I. W.</note> Puritanes, but by themſelues confeſſed, and their owne lawes ſo conuicted: it proueth them for ſuch; but proueth not ſedition, but true and loyall dealing in Catholikes, which doe not ſay with Proteſtants, maſters and martirs, <hi>Wickliffe</hi> and <hi>Huſſe,</hi> and their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers<note place="margin">Concil. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Wickl. artic. Io. Huſſe, &amp;c.</note> Waldenſians; that wicked men in Magiſtracie be deptiued of Rule and Iuriſdiction: but againſt their owne fellowes in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, defend their offices, power, authority and preeminence.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Diſcouerer</hi> will haue the force of this propoſition to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the later ſentence, <hi>(thereby to denie them all ciuill and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Reſpects)</hi> It is both vnproperly ſpoken, and ſlaunderouſly obiected againſt Catholikes; which neither deny to Proteſtants in Authority, or others, any ciuill or naturall Reſpect, for their crimes and ſinnes, neither charge any one amongſt ſo many mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, with Canonicall demerite or impediment of ſuch reſpects.</p>
               <p>Therefore firſt, Such opinions of ſome p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuate Catholiques,
<pb facs="tcp:13233:12"/> 
                  <hi>Andreas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urg.</hi> Mr. <hi>Rainolds,</hi> D. <hi>Gifford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wright.</hi> that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants holde no article of faith, Caluiniſmeis Turciſine, no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>then Turci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me;</hi> compared to <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> is no more then other<note place="margin">Proteſtancy eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h Proteſt deſcribed by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wes. Nichol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n. &amp; Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. Tub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g. in praeſa.</note> Proteſtants ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dge <hi>Caluin</hi> with. And what is this to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of this kingedome, except they meane to bring <hi>Arrianiſme, Neſtorianiſme,</hi> and <hi>Turciſme</hi> into the world, as <hi>Philippus Nicholaus</hi> a lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned proteſtant miniſter, and the proteſtant Deane and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubing write of <hi>Caluin,</hi> &amp; <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nglius.</hi> The re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ited proteſtant hath written a whole Booke of that Subiect, giuing it for Title, <hi>Fundamentorum Caluinianae Sectae cum veteribus Arrianis et Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianis communium Dete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>io.</hi> And yet the Turks Alcoran beeing made by Arrians and Neſtorians (as the Preface there recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth)<note place="margin">Praefat. ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>Caluins</hi> doctrine is proued by him, to agree with them in 17. or 18. chief a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ticles. And in the ſeauenth Chapter he plainly<note place="margin">c. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7 8. 9, 10 11, &amp;c. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r. Cap. 7. ſupr.</note> writeth, that theſe <hi>Caſuiniſts</hi> and <hi>Swinglians</hi> will not be quiet, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they haue brought <hi>Mahumetiſme</hi> and <hi>Turciſme</hi> into the Weſt, as by the <hi>Arrians</hi> and <hi>Neſtorians</hi> it came into the Eaſt. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all people is moſt ielous of the <hi>Sacramentary</hi> Brabenders, Frankes, Heluetians, Engliſh and Scots in this behalfe; and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that <hi>Arrianiſme, Turciſme</hi> and <hi>Swinglianiſme,</hi> be the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Antechriſt.</hi> And he bringeth in <hi>Luther</hi> prophecying (as<note place="margin">Cap 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>upr.</note> he calleth it) that the <hi>Sacramentaries</hi> would neuer ceaſe, vntill they denied Chriſt to be God, which M. <hi>Willet,</hi> D. <hi>Fulke,</hi> and others<note place="margin">Will. Synopſ. contr. gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 19 Fulke in nouo Teſtamento. Conci 1. Nicaen. in Symbol. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il Epheſ. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt. 1. H. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rought. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eruſ. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>up. an. 1604. Will. Antilog. Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. ſup. pag. 2. 3</note> haue almoſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly effected, denying Chriſt to haue receaued his ſubſtance of his Father, or that he is <hi>Deus de deo,</hi> God of God, as the firſt generall Councels haue defined.</p>
               <p>I will next alleadge Mr. H. <hi>Broughton</hi> a late engliſh Proteſtant writer in the laſt yeare, and a man moſt highlie commended by the great recited <hi>Summiſt,</hi> in his new borne <hi>Antilogie;</hi> who telleth his Proteſtant Brethren, or rather Fathers (he ſpeaketh chiefly to the Biſhoppes) in England, that their Tranſlation of Scriptures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to engliſh is ſuch; that <hi>it cauſeth millions of millions to reiect the new Teſtament, and to runne to eternall flames.</hi> In his ſecond Chapter he challengeth their publique tranſlation, of <hi>peruerting the holie text of the olde Teſtament in eight hundred and eight and fourty places.</hi> He telleth the late Archbiſhop of Canterburie, <hi>that he might with as good learning haue ſubſcribed to the Alcoran,</hi> as conſent with ſuch Proteſtants, as he did. He plainly writeth theſe wordes: <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13233:12"/> 
                  <hi>denied in England by publique Authority.</hi> He telleth the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes, that <hi>they betray the Goſpell to the Iewes, and agree with the enemies of our Lord. Their Bible is inferior to the Alcaron. The Biſhopps notes betray our Lord, and Redeemer, and befoole the Rocks of Saluation. They are the very poyſon to all the Goſpell. The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian ſandes may aſwell be reckoned, as Bilſons (the Biſhoppe of winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) Hereſies. He hath a minde to be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mous for millions of errors.</hi> And ſpeaking in his owne perſon ſaieth thus: <hi>I gaue I. C.</hi> (ſo he calles the late proteſtant Archbiſhop of Canterburie) the <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, Maranatha.</hi> No doubt but ſuch a man would excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate a King, if he had come in his way, at that time.</p>
               <p>The admonition to the Parliament written with no ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,<note place="margin">Admonit. patl.</note> vſeth theſe words. <hi>No man in whom there is any ſparke of grace or conſcience, can liue in the common-wealth of England, whoſe inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants be all Infidelles, and they be all Infidelle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that goe to their chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Arch-biſhoppes and Biſhoppes gouernment is both Antichriſtian</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Admonit. 2. pag. 25. 33. Suppl. verſ. 56.</note> 
                  <hi>and deuiliſh. Antichriſt is amonge them. It is traiterous againſt the Maieſtie of Chriſt, It is accurſed. It is an vnlawfull, falſe, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly gouernment. It ſhall be eaſier for Sodome and Gomorrhe in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Admonit. 2. pa. 3</note> 
                  <hi>the day of iudgement, than for the court of Parliament, where the Proteſtant Religion was confirmed. There is no right Religion eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Admonit. 1. pag. 2. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>in England.</hi> I cannot for want of time, and need not for lacke of witnes, recite more teſtimonies in this buſineſſe. Theſe be ſufficient for Catholiques excuſe, and to returne the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vppon Proteſtants. And lett this Obiector vnderſtand, that theſe men which be ſo well conceated of his doctrine, and together teach, that all ſuch ſinnes, and leſſe, deſerue excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication in what perſon ſoeuer, with the penalties thereof; and that they are depoſed from their Seates by ſuch offences, may iuſtly come within the compaſſe of his Concluſion, and <hi>Ergo:</hi> for by his owne allowed maior propoſition, <hi>whoſoeuer doe make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants ſo odious, and unworthy of any ciuill &amp;c. is ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ious, and intollerable amonge Proteſtants:</hi> But as I haue proued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants themſelues, <hi>Proteſtants doe ſo, or be ſuch, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> are ſo to be eſteemed by this Reaſoner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſecond Reaſon anſwered, and returned vpon Protestants.</hi> CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond Reaſon is contained in theſe woordes; <hi>Whoſoeuer do profeſſe any ciuill power ſoueraigne ouer Kings, whether direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or indirectly, are to be accompted ſeditious.</hi> I would wiſh him to except the Emperour of the Princes of Germany, and ſuch as be ſubiect to the Empire, &amp; ſuch caſes. Then to paſſe ouer the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh regiment, I ſay <hi>tranſeat maior</hi> for Chriſtendome: And thus I frame the <hi>minor.</hi> But all Proteſtant writers doe ordinarily both teach and practiſe this Doctrine, as I haue prooued before, and will more plentifully performe heereafter. For this place I onelie inſtance in this vnited kingdome, <hi>Britany,</hi> and principally in two Queene <hi>Maries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt her that raigned in this part which wee inhabite, it was<note place="margin">Proteſtants ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious by this mans Argument</note> the publike conſent of the chiefeſt Proteſtant Biſhoppes and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Sands, Rogers,</hi> and the reſt, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Preachers, That ſhe might be depoſed, and not onelie ſhe, but her ſiſter Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a Proteſtant, and the familie of his Maieſty ſhould be defeated. And was publikely put in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe both with wit and weapons, to the vttermoſt of the greateſt Proteſtants power, the Dukes of Northumberland and Suffolk, and many other of great eſtate. And this not onely contrary to the lawe of God, and the expreſſe Statutes of this kingdome, but their owne oth to the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> when ſhee was Princeſſe in her fathers life. The publike practiſe alſo of Proteſtants in the attempt of ſir <hi>Thomas Wyat,</hi> warranted by the Proteſtant Cleargie, with diuers others in the ſhort regiment of that Queene, may be giuen for inſtance. Therefore let no man obiect heereafter, that the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions<note place="margin">Proteſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s may not condemne their Puritane Brethren.</note> and Practiſes of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bellion proceede onely from the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane Proteſtants; for ſuch pure Proteſtancie had not audience in England at that time, but the defenders there of were called New vp-ſtart arrogant ſpirites by <hi>Latymer,</hi> and ſuch Proteſtants as I<note place="margin">Latim. Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the fixt.</note> haue condemned guiltie in this kinde. And yet the preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Writers of England, which teach, that the true Church can not erre in things eſſentiall to true Religion, and neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and communicate in Sermons, Sacraments, Doctrine, and
<pb facs="tcp:13233:13"/> ſubſcription to articles (the very notes of the Church in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings) cannot condemne theſe traiterous and rebellious poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and practiſes in Puritanes, for great and damnable offences in Religion, or impediments of Saluation: therefore by this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputers Argument, they are to be accounted ſeditious.</p>
               <p>Now I will recite his ſecond propoſition againſt us, which is this. <hi>But all Popiſh prieſts doe profeſſe a double prerogatiue ouer Kings: Democraticall and Monarchicall: namely, both people and Pope: ergo:</hi> To the Popes Authoritie I haue already ſufficientlie anſwered, and will demonſtratiuely proue farther heereafter, that as it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by catholike doctors, it is far more fauorable and defenſiue to Princes titles, then either doctrine or practiſe of Proteſtants, or any other profeſſors of Religion, whereof I haue alſo intreated beefore. Concerning his conceat of Catholikes defending a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocraticall prerogatiue in the people ouer all Kinges: (ſo be his wordes) It fighteth with his owne aſſertion, and preſent poſition of the Popes <hi>Monarchicall prerogatiue ouer all Kings</hi> (which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is his ſentence.) For where there is a Monarchie, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall power or gouernment in one, there is vnposſibillitie of a Democracie and Democraticall Power and Regencie in the people: otherwiſe theſe propoſitions be true: <hi>Kinges be ſubiects to ſubiects, and ſubiects be Kinges of Kinges, ſeruants be maſters to their maſters, Maſters be ſeruants to their ſeruants, Fathers be children of their Children, and Children be fathers to their Fathers:</hi> and the like relations muſt be inuerted by this Logicians Argument.</p>
               <p>But lett vs heare what publique Poſitions he will bring from our Writers, to proue our opinion of a democraticall power in the people ouer Princes, which I haue confuted by his owne propoſition. He only citeth the Author <hi>de iuſta abdicat Henric.</hi> 2 to ſay that <hi>Maieſtas Regni eſt in populo, potius quam in perſona Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis:</hi> That D. <hi>Stapleton</hi> affirmeth, <hi>people are not ordained for the Prince: but the Prince for the people:</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rainolas</hi> to call a King a creature of Mans Creation: the like he citeth out of <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> All which in equall ſence his Maieſtie himſelf in open Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament doth not ſo much ſeeme to diſlike; eſpecially in vacancie of a King or the originall of kingdomes, of which caſes thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors<note place="margin">The kings ſpeach Parli. 1.</note> doe principally entreate. And in ſuch circumſtances I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of this Obiector, whether there euer was, or could be a
<pb facs="tcp:13233:14"/> King, and Ruler ouer people, where there was no people to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or conſent to be ruled. But people both were in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without kings, and made election of diuers kinds of regiment, as they thought fitteſt and moſt ſecure for their defence, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in peace: ſome Monarchicall, ſome Ariſtaraticall, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Democraticall: although none made election of a Monachy by one, and Democracie by the multitude at once in one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, as this ſimple Diſputer did argue before ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces titles; for that is vnpoſſible, as I haue made demonſtration. And his Maieſties wordes be theſe: <hi>Although a Kingdome and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The kings ſpeach ſupt.</note> 
                  <hi>people be Relata<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet can he be no King, if he want people and Subiects:</hi> but there be many people in the world that lacke a head, as when Regall Lines be extinct, people be yet without Kings; but not <hi>e contra:</hi> So where regiment paſſeth by election. In Polonia at the death of euery King, the caſe is ſuch, becauſe that Kingdome and Principallitie goeth by voices: So in Venice: So in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire by the ſeauen Princes, called Princes Electours, ſupplying the peoples ſuffrages, and conſents. And this the Diſcouerer<note place="margin">Rat. 3. infr.</note> himſelfe hath remembred in framing his next Reaſon, wherin he maketh mention of Election, and calleth a ſeditious to hinder the right thereof. But ſlaunders and contradictions be neither wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wickedneſſe, nor vnlearned ignorance in this Accuſer. How the Proteſtants, both clergie and people, claime Soueraignty ouer Princes, is ſpoken before, and often proued in this Treatiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The third Reaſon confuted, and returned.</hi> CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <p>THe maior Propoſition of his third reaſon, is; <hi>Whoſoever vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any pretended Supremacy, whether of Pope or people, doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the neceſſary right of Election, or of Succeſſion of Proteſtant Princes, are to bee holden amongest all Protestants, ſeditious:</hi> his Contradiction in this againſt the former reaſon, I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the laſt Argument. And for this preſent, I grant this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior, and make this my minor: But Proteſtants, and Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,<note place="margin">Proteſtants are ſeditious by this Argument.</note> doe deny the neceſſary right of Election, or Succeſsion of Proteſtant Princes: <hi>ergo;</hi> the minor is proued before in <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Ridley, Latimer, Sandes, Rogers,</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13233:14"/> and <hi>Suffolke,</hi> with their Proteſtant Preachers and forces againſt the Succeſsion of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a Proteſtant, and (though then not borne) his Maieſty a Proteſtant King. I adde further, that his Highneſſe title was expreſly contradicted, and written againſt of purpoſe, in a booke to that end, by <hi>Hales,</hi> (a companion to <hi>Knoxe)</hi> an Engliſh Proteſtant; to which, no Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant (to my knowledge) did euer giue anſwer, or deniall. But ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Catholikes confuted it, as the Catholike Biſhop of <hi>Roſſe,</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and three Catholikes of diſtinct profeſsions in <hi>England;</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>Anthony Browne,</hi> Knight, and Iudge of the common Law, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Morgan,</hi> a Diuine, and Doctor <hi>Mytch,</hi> (or like name) a civill Lawyer.</p>
               <p>Now let vs heare his ſecond propoſition againſt Catholikes, Thus it is: <hi>But all Popiſh Prieſts, doe vtterly aboliſh the title of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, in all Proteſtant Princes, &amp;c. g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>,</hi> This he would proue againſt all Prieſts, becauſe <hi>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>let,</hi> (and conformably to him, Doctor <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton,</hi> Maiſter <hi>Raynolds, Symancha,</hi> and the Author of <hi>Philopatre)</hi> writeth <hi>Nulla eſt Imperatoris, aut Regis Electio, ſi cum Eligitur, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicatus eſt.</hi> The Election of an Emperour or King, is <hi>non,</hi> if he be excommunicate when he is choſen.</p>
               <p>I anſwer: Firſt, heere he contradicteth himſelfe againe, making election and conſent of the people, an eſſentiall thing to Princes titles. Secondly, let all be true which he citeth, and that they ſo teach: yet, if fiue particular men could make a generall councell, and their ſentence be termed a publike poſition; yet they ſpeake onely of a Prince, excommunicate before his Election; which caſe is not now in <hi>rerumnatura,</hi> much leſſe in England. His Maieſty was not excommunicate before his Election, neither is hee now, but is both elected and ſetled in his throne, both without any contradiction of the Pope, and with his <hi>Iubet</hi> of all obedience, and <hi>prohibet</hi> of deniall thereof. All the Catholikes of this Kingedome, applauded it as much as Proteſtants. And his vnion and league with Catholike Princes and people abroad, is ſufficient anſwer, that this is a malicious ſlaunder of holy Prieſthood; and proveth Catholikes innocent, Proteſtants guilty, and this man an vniuſt accuſer.<note place="margin">The Argument retu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned vpon Proteſtants, with a recita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l of their ſeditious doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>But for breuitie, to paſſe ouer forraigne Proteſtants in this place, I will put this diſputer in minde of his brethrens dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb facs="tcp:13233:15"/> principles and poſitions, in this vnited Kingdome. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Writers and Preachers of <hi>England</hi> defended, that <hi>Wyat</hi> was no Traytor to Queene <hi>Mary.</hi> And thus they wrote expreſly; <hi>It is lawfull to kill Kings, and both by Gods law, and mans law, Queene</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Goodm pag 103 obed pa. 99. 113. Goodm. pa. 99.</note> Mary <hi>ought to be put to death,</hi> (what Prieſt of <hi>England</hi> did ever ſo write, ſpeake, or thinke of any Proteſtant his Soueraigne?) <hi>ſhe was a tyrant, a monſter, a cruell beaſt.</hi> And yet the purer ſort of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants affirmd of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (as his Lordſhip of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hay an. pag. 13 15. 23. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing. poli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. 133. 134. ſup.</note> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſſeth) <hi>That ſhe was worſe then her ſiſter</hi> Many, <hi>and they more ſuppreſſed by her, then by the other.</hi> They did write; <hi>That ſhe was not to be obeyed, being againſt their proceedings, and openly moued the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egents in</hi> England, <hi>to take armes againſt her; affirming, if they</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Suppli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. to the gouer. of Wales pa. 16. 36, 37, 38, 39 D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng. poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. lib 4 e. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4 Goodm p. 144. 145. Obed. pag 110. Knos. hiſt. pag. 37 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. pag 99. 103. 104. Goodm. pa. 99. Buchan. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g pag. 40. 58 Obed. pa. 111</note> 
                  <hi>refuſed it, they ceaſed to be Magiſtrates.</hi> Theſe alſo inſuing, be more of their holy dogmaticall principles. <hi>Euill Princes, ought by the law of God, to be depoſed, and inferior Magiſtrates ought to doe it cheefely: It is lawfull to kill wicked Kings: It were good that rewards were appointed by the people, for ſuch as kill tyrants, as commonly there are, for thoſe that haue killed eyther woolues, or beares, or taken their whelpes. The people haue the ſame power ouer their King, that the King hath ouer any one perſon. Iudges ought by the law of God, to ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Princes before them, and to proceede againſt them, as againſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offenders: the people may arraigne the Prince: the Miniſters may</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Buchan. pa. 62 Cartwr. replic. 2. pag. 65. Obed. pag. 115. 116. Bucha. p. 70.</note> 
                  <hi>excommunicate him: any Miniſter may excommunicate the greatest Prince: he that is excommunicate, is not worthy to enioy any life vpon earth.</hi> Whereby is euident, the monſtrous diſſimulation of this people, which ſometimes, for their aduantage, will not be ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to denie, that with other articles of their religion, and the cheefeſt, and to ſay; that they onely claime power to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, not to depoſe and kill Princes. And to teſtifie how eaſily,<note place="margin">Suru. pretend. holy D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cipl. pag. 283. 284. Buchan. pag. 6 13. Obed. pag. 25</note> and for what ordinary offences Princes may be thus intreated, the preſent Proteſtant Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> is witneſſe, that fornication, drunkenneſſe, ſwearing, curſing, fighting, chiding, brawling, breaking of the Sabbath, wanton and vaine words, and the like, be ſufficient incitements and cauſes of ſuch proceedings with them. And they tell vs further; <hi>That the people are better then the King, and of greater authority: the people haue right to beſtow the Crowne at their pleaſure: the authority which Princes haue, is giuen them from the people, and the people may take it away againe, as men may</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13233:15"/> 
                  <hi>reuoke their Proxies, and letters of Attorney.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I would demand of this obiector, whether they be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Roman Catholike Church, or the pillars of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Congregation, that congregateth and gathereth together ſuch monſters as holy children, which teacheth a double prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue ouer Princes: one in the people, when inferior Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and not Magiſtrates may, (and muſt by their doctrine) depoſe Kings and Soueraignes: and likewiſe their miniſtery, (as before) hath as ample, or a more preeminent authority. Which alſo concluded from theſe Engliſh Proteſtant principles; <hi>If Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates tranſgreſſe Gods lawes themſelues, and commaund others to doe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Goodm. pa. 119. 139.</note> 
                  <hi>the like, then haue they loſt that honour and obedience, which otherwiſe their ſubiects did owe vnto them, and ought no more to be taken for Magiſtrates, but to be examined, condemned, and puniſhed, as priuate tranſgreſſors. When Magiſtrates doe ceaſe to doe their duties the people are as it were without officers, and then God giueth the ſword into their</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pa. 185. 180. 184</note> 
                  <hi>hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſuch was the vniuerſall practiſe of all proteſtants (eſpecially Calueniſts) in all places of their holy preaching, <hi>Germany, Helue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Denmarke, France, England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> with others in fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mer times: and at this preſent, the Proteſtants in <hi>Hungary, Tranſiluania, Sweueland,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> in actuall ſedition and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt their Soueraignes, Emperour, King, and Princes, are inſtance.</p>
               <p>Concerning that ſpirituall ſupremacy, which the lawes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Kings ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy denyed by all Puritans, and e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, or doubted of by al engliſh prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant writers.</note> atrribute to his Maieſtie, it can be no queſtion, but all Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans doe deny it; which not onely teach a ſuperior power, both in people and Miniſters, to which the reſt of the Proteſtants of the ſame congregation, (as before) muſt needes conſent: But alſo in this regard, that the gouernment of their Elderſhip, or Bresbitery, (incompoſible with Princes Supremacy) is the cheefeſt article of their religion, and diſtinctiue note of their reformed Church.</p>
               <p>Then to come to the preſent Proteſtant writers, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignements, the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> is the man which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth<note place="margin">Suru. of pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cipl.</note> relation, that this was a common propoſition: <hi>Princes haue no more to doe with matters of the Church, then the Miniſters haue with the affaires of the Common-wealth.</hi> And there it is alleaged<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſuch gouernment by Princes, is worſe then by the Pope, for diuers rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons<note place="margin">Pa. 25<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 253. 254 255 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>6 &amp;c. ſup.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13233:16"/> there recited, and not confuted by any Proteſtant: I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the ſentences of the principall.</p>
               <p>Proteſtants of this time, Doctor <hi>Fulke</hi> in plaine termes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth,<note place="margin">D Fulke h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>br. c 13 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect 9. 1. pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 2. v. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ct 5. Ioh. c. 21. 1. petr. 5. Mat. c. 16. Bell. mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iu. lib. 2. fol. 78, 79. 80. 81 Suru. part. 3. c. 10 pa. 426. &amp; 1. part. pag 34. Whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ker contra Bellar controu. 1. q 8. D. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. li. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</note> that Emperours and Kings, owe obedience to the Clergy, and cannot preſcribe lawe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Religion to Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, by their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Maiſter <hi>Bell</hi> writeth the Eccleſiaſticall affaires to be in the Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgy, as to decide controuerſies, and that the King hath on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge and authority, to command the Miniſters to preach, and giueth him no definitiue ſentence. Doctor <hi>Whitaker</hi> is all for the priuate ſpirit, and bringeth diuers reaſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all peculiar for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Such alſo is Doctor <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liues</hi> ſentence; and yet he addeth, that generall Counſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls are abſolutely neceſſary: then Kings iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments not ſufficient: And a generall Counſell (none yet among them) neceſſary b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore their religion may be approued. Maiſter <hi>Hooker,</hi> and Docter <hi>Couell,</hi> make the Eccleſiaſticall power ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame<note place="margin">Hooker l. 5. eccl. Polit c. 77. D. Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uel. c. 4. Defence of Hooker pl. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noc c. 1. D. Dow. ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. cont. Bellat. Bilſ. tit. li. true. Differ. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Synopſ. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trou 7. 9. 1.</note> in ſuch buſineſſe, and the Temporall, to be dependant and ſubordinate. Doctor <hi>Downam</hi> aſſigneth the Princes office to maintaine the truth, ſuppoſed to be otherwiſe determined. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> ſaith; that the Princes lawfull power is to command for truth. Maiſter <hi>Willet</hi> telleth vs; that the Prince in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is neither the myſticall head, nor miniſteriall head, but a politike head of the Church, and to ſee that euery member doe his office and dutie; and he vſeth theſe words: <hi>Neither doe we giue vnto the Prince abſolute power (then no ſupremacy) to make eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lawes.</hi> And his Maieſty is witneſſe, that many other Proteſtant<note place="margin">Confer. 14 Ian. an. 1603. p. 82. 83</note> Preachers before him, were content to paſſe ouer that title with ſilence, which they would not performe in ſuch audience, if in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion they did maintaine that ſupreame eccleſiaſticall preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue in Princes. And to adde one former example more: Doctor<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e againſt Barrow &amp; Green<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wood, &amp;c. p. 17. 18</note> 
                  <hi>Some</hi> writeth thus: <hi>The greateſt Prince whatſoever, is to obey ſuch as teach them out of Gods booke.</hi> And doth not diſallow this ſentence in ſuch ſence. <hi>From this ohedience there is no exception nor exemption of Kings, nor Princes, be they neuer ſo great, if they haue ſoules, and be Chriſtian men, they muſt be ſubiect to ſome Biſhop, Prieſt, or other Prelate.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The fourth Reaſon confuted, and returned</hi> CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THe fourth Reaſon is thus deliuered. <hi>When the King is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in his Throne by common conſent of the Kingdome:</hi> (here alſo is a contradiction to his ſecond reaſon, which doth not allow of ſuch conſent) <hi>Whoſoere ſhall manacle the handes of his ſubiects, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting all obedience, may iuſtly by order of law be chalenged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for a diſordered and rebellious perſon.</hi> This is the firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,<note place="margin">The Argument returned vpon Proteſtants</note> which I graunt vnto, and thereby I frame this ſecond: But ordinarily Proteſtant preachers and profeſſors doe thus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle the hands of Subiects, and detract all obedience as is moſt manifeſt in their publike poſitions and practiſes before, and more amply to be recited hereafter: <hi>Ergo:</hi> they may iuſtly by order of law be challenged and condemned for diſordered and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebellious perſons.</p>
               <p>Let vs heare the reſt of his Silogiſme: <hi>All Popiſh prieſts,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Prieſts cleered, and prooued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</note> 
                  <hi>do diſſolue the oth of obedience to all Protestant gouernors: Ergo,</hi> How ſlaunderous and falſe this aſſumption is, I haue proued before; and the duetifull behauiour of Catholikes in all partes of the worlde to their Proteſtant Princes, not any at this preſent with conſent of their prieſtes denying obedience, (the caſe of Proteſtant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Subiects in diuerſe places, being in contrary practiſe and experience,) giueth condemnation to his Aſser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion. Secondly, all the Authorities which he bringeth from Cardinall <hi>Tollet, Maſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius,</hi> and others, priuate men, intreate of ſuch as be <hi>nominatim</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate. In which ſtate there is not any one Proteſtant go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor at this time; neyther can any iuſt feare thereof be reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly apprehended, by the Popes generall proceedings in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, except any Proteſtant prince (which God forbid) ſhoulde be incited by ſuch vnchriſtian ſpirites as this Diſcouerer ſeemeth to be poſſeſſed with, to exceede all others in perſecuting Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, or offering indignities to the church of Chriſt. Thirdly, I anſwer, that the opinions of <hi>Tollet, Maſſouius, Panormitane, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorius de Valentia, Bannes,</hi> and the Author of <hi>Philopater</hi> (all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Writers hee aleadgeth in this place) though they did approue
<pb facs="tcp:13233:17"/> (as they doe deſtroy) his conceit; yet ſuch priuate men can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make a dogmaticall principle, nor publike poſition, by which his promiſe was to make probation. And in this his affirming, <hi>That all prieſts doe diſſolue the oath of obedience to all Proteſtant Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors, the Authority which bindeth them all to ſuch opinion, can be no leſſe, then a Dogmaticall and publique Doctrine,</hi> And theſe may alſo ſuffice for his next obiections, from the practiſe of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. <hi>Pius</hi> 5. and <hi>Gregory</hi> 9. To whom I farther aunſwere in particular.</p>
               <p>And firſt to <hi>Gsegory</hi> the 7. who as this man vrgeth, abſolued all from obedience to Excommunicates. I anſwer for all Catholikes in generall: That this nothing concerned Proteſtants, then not thought of in the world, neither any hereticks (then not raigning)<note place="margin">Fox to. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Mon. in Greg 7. Will. Antil Genebr. Chron in Greg. 7. Plat in Greg. 7.</note> but only ſuch as he had other quarrells and contentions againſt.</p>
               <p>But he vrgeth the gloſſe vppon <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, to haue both excommunicated all hereticks, and to haue abſolued ſubiects from their obedience, and citeth for his authority, <hi>Greg.</hi> 9. <hi>Pont. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Decret. tit.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>gloſſa.</hi> I anſwer that in the place allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged<note place="margin">Decr. per Greg. 13.</note> there is no mention of any ſuch matter, or any thing like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: only there is cited the Affrican Councell in theſe words. <hi>Si quis Epiſcopus heredes inſtituerit extraneos à conſanguinitate ſua, vel haereticos etiam conſanguineos aut Paganos praetulerit ſaltem poſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ei Anathema dicatur, atque eius nomen inter Dei Sacerdotes nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo modo recitetur.</hi> And this Canon both for ſubſtance and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity oppoſeth it ſelfe againſt him.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, he brings againe the Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> the fift againſt Q. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth. To which, anſwere is made before: whereto I adde, that many graue and learned men haue affirmed the information of the caſe of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to the Apoſtolique <hi>See,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon that cenſure of excommunication was awarded againſt her, to haue been vntrue. And that <hi>Pius</hi> the fift then Pope, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictor thereof, an holy man, bewailed the proceedings vppon ſuch ſuggeſtion. And that many Catholikes of both conditions, were both ſory for the cenſure, &amp; it was defended by D. <hi>Sanders,</hi> D. <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtow</hi> or any other Ingliſh writer, rather wiſhing the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie betwixt two Superiors th'one temporall, th'other ſpirituall, had bin reſerued to the high Tribunal in heauen (then ſo ſubiect to many iealoſies) had been ſo proſecuted in earth: among which, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:13233:17"/> 
                  <hi>Allane</hi> writeth of that matter in theſe wordes. <hi>Hoc tamen ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Card. Allen. ad per. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>multos Catholicos illud factum agre tuliſſe, optaſseque omninò vt ea res tam grauis, varijſque obnoxia ſuſpitionibus, literis commiſſa nunquam fuiſſet, ſed ſublimioribus Poteſtatibus, Deique potiſſimum Iudicio reſeruata, vt vel in hoc ſeculo, vel in altero, cum &amp; Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; Principes rationem reddent villicationis ſuae, de hac re contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſia decideret inter noſtros Superiores.</hi> Notwithſtanding, this we know, that many Catholikes did thinke hardly of that deed, and did wiſh, that if ſo great a matter and ſubiect to diuers ſuſpitions, had neuer bin committed to writing, but reſerued to higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and moſt chiefly to the iudgement of God, that either in this world or in the world to come, when both Popes and Princes muſt render account of their Bailifewicke, the controue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſie of this matter ſhould be tried betweene our Superiors. Then, if the caſe was ſuch, between the Pope, and that deceaſed Princes; I cannot conceaue, how any equally minded Proteſtant can be of minde, that the Pope ſo ſtrictlie commaunding obedience of all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes in England to his Maieſtie, will, or can be ſo contrarie vnto himſelfe, to publiſh a contrarie commaund againſt a King, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in publique Parliament, to meet with the Roman Church<note place="margin">Kings ſpeach parliam. 1.</note> all Nouelties taken away (we wiſh no more) and in the meane time acknowledging the ſame Roman Church to be our Mother Church, and that his minde was euer free from perfection or thralling his ſubiects in matters of couſcience. Of ſuch a King, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf cited againſt vs will be witnes, that he thinketh<note place="margin">Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lar. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib. 5. de Rom. pont. c. 7</note> the Pope cannot ſo proceed againſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fift Reaſon confuted, and returned.</hi> CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>THe fift Reaſon is nothing in effect, but the former confuted: now againe repeated with malice, and ſuting alſo with the three next enſuing, and is thus obiected:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer ſuggeſteth a Doctrine of forcible depoſing of Princes from their thrones, are therein manifeſtly rebellious.</hi> Let vs grant this <hi>Maior</hi> Propoſition: then thus I make my <hi>Minor.</hi> But Proteſtants be ſuch, as both their publike opinions and practiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s before, and
<pb facs="tcp:13233:18"/> after conuince. <hi>Ergo,</hi> they are manifeſtly rebellious by this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puter.</p>
               <p>Now let vs heare what dogmaticall authority, principle, or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition he produceth to iuſtifie his accuſation: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t all Popiſh Prieſts (his phraſe) defend and approue theſe things. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I haue confuted this in the former, yet I will rather mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply repetitions, then leaue any ſuſpicion behinde me, to omit any of his oppoſitions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the violent depoſing of Kings and Emperours, hee citeth <hi>Coſterus,</hi> to ſay; That the power to depoſe Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, was euer in the Popes of <hi>Rome; penes Romanos pontifices,</hi> which he tranſlateth peculiar to the Pope. But he muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that here is no ſpeach of violence, violent depoſing, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſing, which is his propoſition to be proued. We will proceede. He citeth <hi>Molma</hi> to ſay; that, <hi>Depoſitio Imperatoris ex iuſta cauſa pertinet ad ſummum Pontificem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But firſt againe, heere is no ſpeech of force or violence, and ſo not to your purpoſe. Secondly, there is at this preſent, a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene the Emperour which is created by the Popes<note place="margin">I. Cerem. Rom. eccl. in Coron. Imperat.</note> lawes, and with his ſolemnities, and from whom he receiueth his ſword: and a King that is abſolute, &amp; not ſo created, or depending for power or iuriſdiction, ſuch as our Soueraigne in <hi>England</hi> is. And <hi>Molina</hi> himſelfe, cited in this place by our accuſer, inſinuateth the ſame d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſparitie and reaſon in theſe words: <hi>Quia Imperator eſt tanquam miniſter ſummi pontificis, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe the Emperour is as it were the Popes Miniſter, exerciſing the ſword of Iuriſdiction at his will; <hi>ad natum ſummi pontificis:</hi> which is altogether vntrue of his Maieſtie, not ſo receiuing or exerciſing authority.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Bellarmine</hi> I haue anſwered before, that his opinion is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this diſcouerer. For hee alloweth not of cenſures againſt Princes, where they grow not to violence and perſecution. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Doctor <hi>Saunders</hi> and <hi>Philopater,</hi> I haue already ſpoken ſufficiently, and yet their citations doe not conclude violence in the caſe of excommunicates, whereof they intreat. <hi>Bannes</hi> alleaged to defend; That an Apoſtata King, may be depoſed by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, meaneth ſuch a Prince as <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowncer of Chriſtianity, which is properly termed Apoſtata. And conformable is the Allegation from <hi>Simancha,</hi> which be all
<pb facs="tcp:13233:18"/> the authorities hee bringeth to binde all Popiſh (his Epitheton) Prieſts to defend violent depoſing of Kings: which not one of thoſe particular writers affirme, but was both the publike opinion &amp; practiſe of proteſtants, in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l opportunities &amp; occaſions, as is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten remembred in this defence.</p>
               <p>Now let vs heare the ſuppoſed publike practiſe in this point. He alleageth three authorities only of particular men, which ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence be not ſufficient to pronounce their iudgement or allowance to be publike. But let them be vrged to his greateſt aduantage. The firſt is, againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France,</hi> excommunicate, from the Author <hi>De iuſta abdic. Henr.</hi> 3. affirming onely; that the French ſubiects which armed aganſt him, did it <hi>ſecura conſcientia,</hi> with ſecure conſcience, as againſt a violater of publike faith, <hi>viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore publicae fidei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer: firſt, this is no Engliſh caſe, except this diſcouerer will inrole his Maieſtie in the number of excommunicates, and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of publike fidelitie, which is moſt iniurious to his Highneſſe, and in Catholikes, would be called trecherous. And yet this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor doth onely affirme; that they did it, or might doe it in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. But hee doth not iuſtifie (which this man muſt generally proue) that all thoſe, and the reſt of the French ſubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts, were bound in conſcience to take Armes againſt him: and yet, if he had ſo ſaid, there is an euident inequality aſſigned betweene the caſes in compariſon.</p>
               <p>His ſecond authority, is an opinion of Diuines, in a Colledge at <hi>Salaman,</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> (no publike authoritie, if true) that all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes which did not follow the <hi>O-neale,</hi> did ſinne mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tally. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> then being excommunicate, and that <hi>Xiſtus quintus</hi> did rather allow, then app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue their opinion. But firſt, who ſeeth not the diſparity of thoſe Princes, before compared. Secondly, that ſchoole followed their information; which being vntrue, their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence faileth, which the experience it ſelfe of that time, conuinceth: for moſt Catholikes practiſed the contrary to that iudgement, reſiſted <hi>O-neele,</hi> and defended Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> And <hi>Xiſtus quintus,</hi> neuer did ſee the reſolution of that ſchoole. The practiſes of Proteſtants, are no nouelties in ſuch affaires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſixt Reaſon confuted, and returned.</hi> CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>THus he proceedeth to his ſixt Reaſon: <hi>Whoſoeuer doe intend, deſigne, or practiſe the murther of Princes, muſt neceſſarily be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for deſperate Traytors.</hi> This is the <hi>Maior</hi> propoſition which I grant, and thus proceede in forme: But <hi>Luther, Munſter, Suinglius, Caluine, Bezae, Spiphanius, Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Sands, Knoxe, Goodman,</hi> and other Cleargie Proteſtants, with their Adherents and Diſciples, did intend, deſigne; and (ſo much as they could) practiſe ſuch impietie, as I haue demonſtratiuely proued. <hi>Ergo,</hi> they muſt neceſſarily, by this mans argument, be holden for deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Traytors.</p>
               <p>But againſt Catholikes he vrgeth: That all popiſh Prieſts, are guilty in ſome of theſe kindes: that is, intending, deſigning, or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing the murther of Princes. <hi>Ergo,</hi> I anſwer, that the late Lord Treaſurer, reputed the Author of the booke intituled, <hi>The execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iuſtice, &amp;c.</hi> was thought, in his daies, to be a man, not ſecond to many in politicall wiſedome, and affaires of Common-wealth: And I thinke, much to be preferr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d before this Diſcouerer, for<note place="margin">Execut. of Iuſt.</note> place and wiſedome, and yet he will tell vs the quite contrary, to this aſſertion; That there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re many Catholike Prieſts and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops alſo in this kingdome, which, although they were depriued of their preferments, and impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oned by Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> yet they were ſo farre from being contained within the circuite of this mans propoſition, that they be dignified by that wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler, with theſe titles; faithfull and quiet ſubiects, very quiet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, inclined to dutifulneſſe to the Queenes Maieſty, and the like. And for ſuch, hee reciteth very many famous men, Doctor <hi>Heath</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Doctor <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oole,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Peterbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> Doctor <hi>Tunſtall,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Wincheſter, Carlile, Ely, Lincolne,</hi> together with Abbots, Deanes, &amp;c. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by this authority, the obiecters generall propoſition, of all Prieſts guiltineſſe, cannot be true. But he vrgeth; That all Prieſts profeſſe it lawfull to take Armes againſt their Kings; and what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning (ſaith he) can Armes haue, but blood?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:19"/>
               <p> I haue anſwered him before that this is falſe, by the cheefe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants declaration of many Prieſts quietneſſe, loyalty, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Secondly, I tell this diſputer, that he hath made a ſound argument, to proue all the Proteſtant Miniſters of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lund, France, Heluetia, Germany, Sweueland,</hi> and other Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, with their confederate Proteſtants, conuinced of ſedition, for taking, or perſwading Armes againſt their Soueraignes, to be likewiſe guilty of the blood and murther of thoſe Princes, in their deſignements.</p>
               <p>If Armes can haue no other meaning but onely blood, as this bloody Sentencer affirmeth; for all the world can witneſſe that they tooke Armes againſt their Rulers: But againſt Catholikes, which know both an offenſiue, and defenſiue warre, his bloody iudgement can giue no deadly wound, though he had prooued (which is moſt falſly ſpoken) that all Prieſts profeſſe it lawfull to take Armes againſt their Kings: which I haue before returned vpon the Proteſtant profeſſion. And yet how doubtfully, and with equiuocation, (againſt which, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> argueth in his ninth Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) doth he ſpeake in this place: neither expreſſing in what caſe, or againſt what Prince, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes are defended lawfull.</p>
               <p>But I will anſwer him (as before) except he will make his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty (for whom hee would ſeeme to pleade) an vſurping Tyrant, an Apoſtata from Chriſtian faith, incorrigible in impiety, and a monſter (as it were) among men, it is a proteſtant doctrine, and no Catholike opinion, that either blood muſt be exacted, or Armes taken againſt a Prince.</p>
               <p>Seeing his owne reputation hath no happier ſucceſſe, let vs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine his authorities. He firſt bringeth the Author of <hi>Iuſt. abdic. Hen.</hi> 3, to ſay; that <hi>Tyrannum occidere honeſtum eſt:</hi> it is honeſt to kill a Tyrant. Well, then King <hi>Iames</hi> is a Tyrant by this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: otherwiſe, both he and his Author, be Iudges againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; for that writer expreſly nameth a Tyrant. And to ſhew this mans further dutifull affection to his Prince, hee muſt meane an<note place="margin">Reade Peter N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. Domin. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o, Cuner, and others.</note> vſurping Tyrant, which is no King, but an intrudor: for by the common opinion, ſuch a Tyrant is vnderſtoode in this caſe, by the generall Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> to which, that Author, and all Catholikes muſt giue aſſent, and yeelde obedience. But ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines (as this diſcouerer) which are aboue generall Councells, the
<pb facs="tcp:13233:20"/> whole Church of Chriſt, and all authority, may make Tyrants of whom they liſt, and depoſe Princes at their pleaſures. And this futeth beſt with their holy ſpirit: For if euery man among them, may iudge of all Fathers, Popes, Councells, Scriptures, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, which be the higheſt, they may with leſſe preſumption, ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llenge to be Superiors, and ſit in iudgement of all terrene, and temporall buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>He bringeth no other authors for prieſts intending, deſigning or practiſing the murther of Princes, but onely citeth Mr. <hi>Rainolds, Gregorius de valentia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Simancha</hi> about cenſured heretickes, often before anſwered in his ſence and meaning: But his holy obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and duty can finde no other company in the chriſtian world, for his King, and Soueraigne, but Tirants, excommunicate he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes, and ſuch exploded perſons.</p>
               <p>For practiſe in this point, he only alleadgeth three authoriiies, beſides this late vnhappie Stratageme. His firſt teſtimony is from <hi>Gallobelgicus,</hi> who among other of his farre fetched intelligences ſhould affirme, that one <hi>Arnolde</hi> in Paris aſcribed the Tirannie of the Spaniards in the Indies, to the Ieſuites. But <hi>Lewis Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, Metellus Sequanus</hi> and others of greater credite, who ſpeake dolefully, and bitterlie againſt that Tirannie, be of other minde: And we intreate now of Chriſtian Princes, and not of poore Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell and Pagan common people. Therefore if this were true, yet to no purpoſe, if there were no prieſts but Ieſuites. But it is well knowne that <hi>Arnoldus</hi> was a profeſſed enemy to that Societie, and is confuted by <hi>Montanus</hi> and others. And yet <hi>Gallobelgicus</hi> is not without his hiperbolicall Locutions.</p>
               <p>His ſecond example is, that <hi>Rodolphu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Comes,</hi> (which he tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth Duke <hi>Rodolph)</hi> foght againſt the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate. To which he ioyneth the often repeated Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> the fift againſt Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> both anſwered before. And ſtill this man cannot ballaunce his Soueraigne with any but excommunicates, Indian infidells, Tirants, Apoſtataes &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Laſtly; he addeth the late conſpiracie againſt the houſe of Parliament. But as he hath heard, that all prieſts were not ſo well pleaſed in the former proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dings with the deceaſed Queene: So I truſt they will be innocent in ſo vile a practiſe againſt our preſent Soueraigne; And it is moſt certaine that this example ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:13233:20"/> not for his purpoſe, of prouing all prieſts to intend, deſigne, or practiſe ſuch things. For firſt, the cheefeſt prieſt the Pope had abſolutely fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bidden all diſobedience, and ſtrictly commanded obedience vnto his Maieſty, by Engliſh Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, prieſts, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by his abſolute power of ſpirituall ſuperiority, as by theſe words; <hi>Quia Papaiubet,</hi> the obedience, and <hi>prohibe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. The cheefe ſuperior of prieſts in <hi>England,</hi> in ſpirituall things, the Archprieſt had ſo receiued, and promulged the ſame command long ſince, in Auguſt laſt. And vpon his firſt notice of the pretended wickedneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> condemned it by his particular letters for an intollerable, vncharitable, ſcandalous, and deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te fact, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the order of holy Church, againſt the preſcript of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell, againſt the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntence of the beſt writers of this age, againſt the Popes commandement: and conſorting with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> (the proteſtant Saint and Martyr) condemned in the Catholike generall councell at <hi>Conſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then, if the ſecular prieſts of <hi>England</hi> will acknowledge, eyther the Archprieſt for their ſuperior at home, or the Pope at <hi>Rome,</hi> (as all, both regular and others muſt doe) neyther all the prieſts of this Nation, nor any one (except diſobedient to his ſuperior) was guilty of this conſpiracy, or did, or doth eyther intend, deſigne, or practiſe ſuch irreligious wickedneſſe. And both holy and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py is that religion to be eſteemed, among whoſe profeſſors in this<note place="margin">The di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>courſe of the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e intended treaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</note> Kingdome, ſo many thouſands, and in the daies of ſo manifold diſgraces and miſeries for that faith, ſo ſmall a company of cheefeſt Agents, or Aſsiſtants are charged with that offence.</p>
               <p>Wee haue heard, read, ſeene, and taſted of many conſpiracies and rebellions by proteſtants, and more and greater by them, (proportion of time and Countries obſerued) where both Kings, whole kingdomes, and Common-weales, haue beene put in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and yet they were dogmaticall men in that profeſſion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Prophets, Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, and conſpired thouſands for euery one particular perſon in this recited: and yet their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies were not condemned by their Preachers and Doctors, but iuſtified and applauded, not forbidden, but commanded by their ſpirituall maiſters, and their rebells, ſlaine in ſuch actuall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions againſt Princes, not reproued, but approued and canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed for holy Martyrs. When all things be contrary in this caſe,
<pb facs="tcp:13233:21"/> by the proteſtant diſourſe it ſelfe of this tragedy. And if proofe can be made, of any one of holy prieſtly order, to haue beene an Agent in ſo vnholy buſineſſe, he will be as much abandoned of all good prieſts and Catholikes, as of the proteſtants themſelues, for that diſloyalty. The ignominy and perpetuall reproach wherewith the names of vnhappy <hi>Watſon,</hi> and <hi>Clarke</hi> are ſtained, with all of our religion, will be a witneſſe in any caſe of like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſeuenth Reaſon confuted, and returned.</hi> CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>HIs ſeuenth Sillogiſme is this: <hi>Seeing it is in a manner all one to commit a villante, and to commend it, we may argue, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall iuſtifie acts of treaſons and parricides, are not vnguilty of the ſame crimes.</hi> To this I grant, and adde, (which is euidently proued before) that the cheefeſt teachers and profeſſors of Proteſtancy, doe not onely iuſtifie, but commend, canonize for holy, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, command, and reward ſuch proceedings: therefore they are not vnguilty of the ſame crimes.</p>
               <p>And whereas he ſetteth downe for his leſſe Propoſition: <hi>But all Prieſts doe iuſtifie ſuch heinous parricides. Ergo,</hi> I haue proued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, both by their owne authority, continuall experience, and at this time, that ſuch aſſertions be moſt falſe and ſlanderous.</p>
               <p>But hee will maintaine his ſentence, becauſe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith; Many Popes haue worthily depriued many Princes, of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall authority. The examples be in <hi>Leo</hi> 3. <hi>Fredericke</hi> 1. <hi>Otho</hi> 5. and <hi>Childericke,</hi> King of <hi>France.</hi> To Obiections of which nature, I haue often anſwered before. And ſincere dealing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged the true cauſes of ſuch proceſſe, with thoſe Princes, which take away the enuie of this matter, proue a flat diſparitie in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes compared, and bring eternall ſhame to many Proteſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, and often depoſing Princes for meaner quarrells, and for no true cauſe at all. The rebellions and attempts be too many to be recited. The examples of Princes depoſed, or depriued of their Kingdomes, Countries, or territories, by Proteſtants, (meaner then Popes) be more in ſo ſhort a time, then in all the papall gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:13233:21"/> Queene <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Enfanta</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> the Emperor in diuers parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> and elſewhere, in former time, the preſent Emperour in <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Tranſyluania,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Geneua,</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Embden,</hi> Duke of <hi>Loraine,</hi> king of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> king of <hi>France,</hi> king of <hi>Sweueland,</hi> in their territories ſurprized, inuaded, taken, ſold to enemies, or kept by rebbells, (no ſuch thing in the Popes caſes, neuer making themſelues the richer by others loſſes) yeelde teſtimony in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe.</p>
               <p>Next commeth in a <hi>gratias agimus,</hi> for the death of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France,</hi> by the Author of the booke, <hi>de iuſta abdicat. Hen.</hi> 3. which was a Catholike. But I tell him, that alſo a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, Doctor <hi>Barkeley,</hi> a profeſſor at <hi>Muſſipont,</hi> hath confuted that booke, which alſo may ſerue for other citations from thence, which I haue anſwered before.</p>
               <p>He accuſeth Cardinall <hi>Alane,</hi> for approuing the rendering of <hi>Dauontore,</hi> vnto the hands of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the true owner. By which, he condemneth himſelfe, to be within the compaſſe of his owne concluſion of rebellion, and to iuſtifie ſuch acts of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: for all the world can witneſſe, that Towne truly to belong to that King. Then, not the ſurrendering of it to the lawfull Prince, (which hee condemneth) but the wrongfull withholding of it, (which he approueth) was treaſon and rebellion.</p>
               <p>And ſuch as this diſcouerer is, ſuch alſo the reſt of his Clergy proteſtant brethren in <hi>England,</hi> muſt bee eſteemed, euen in this point: for in their name, the firſt defence of thoſe diſobedient and ſeditious Netherlanders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was vndertaken. And ſo, both by publike poſitions, and practiſes, they teach and iuſtifie actes of treaſon, and rebellion, both in themſelues, and their euangelicall brethren, ſo many yeares, in ſo many diſloyall attempts, rapines, intruſions, diſ-inheritings, depoſings, piracies, murthers, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameſt outrages, againſt their naturall and true Soueraignes; and not in one onely act and oration, (one of <hi>Gallobelgicus</hi> exceſſiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes) made of the death of <hi>Henry</hi> the third in <hi>France. Ergo,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtanrs are not vnguilty of theſe crimes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The eight Reaſon confuted, and returned vpon Proteſtants.</hi> CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>THus he frameth his next Argument. <hi>Thoſe Snakes that do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> naturally ſting, ſo ſoone as they get warmth, may not be harbored in the boſome of the Common-wealth.</hi> To which propoſition I ſay, <hi>concedo:</hi> &amp; further adde by ſuch aſſertion, that the proteſtant Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and profeſſors of the reformed Churches, may not be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored in any kingdome, or ciuill Country: for they are proued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, naturally to ſting, (and kill, if they can) ſo ſoone as they haue obtained power to performe it. Which I will now alſo, more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully demonſtrate in this chapter, when I haue exempted Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes from the accuſation, in the ſecond propoſition; which is: <hi>But all Prieſts profeſſe rebellions, as ſoone as they can preſume of their ſtrength. Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His cheefeſt proofe of this, is from <hi>Bannes,</hi> who (as he telleth vs) teacheth; that a King may be depoſed, where there is <hi>euidens noticia criminis,</hi> euident knowledge of his ſinne. I anſwer; That ſuch opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is to be reproued, as againſt, not onely <hi>Cunerus Nauarre, &amp;c.</hi> but the great Laterane generall Councell, to which, <hi>Bannes,</hi> and all Catholikes, muſt ſubmit their ſentences: which alſo diſchargeth vs of this forged ſlaunder, and condemneth the accuſer, of vniuſt calumniation.</p>
               <p>But he vrgeth further from the ſame Author, holding the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Catholikes excuſed; <hi>quia non ſe eximunt ex ſuperiorum poteſtate, nec bellum contra eos gerunt: quia non ſuppetunt illis vires, ob ſequentia pericula:</hi> which this diſcouerer thus tranſlateth; The Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, who now doe not take Armes againſt the Proteſtants, are excuſed, becauſe they want ſufficient power. I anſwer: If this be the opinion of <hi>Bannes,</hi> he ſpeaketh ignorantly in this caſe: For the Pope himſelfe, <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth, had declared, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the vnl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned, that wee might performe all duties of obedience, notwithſtanding any cenſure. And this we may proue by the next obiection it ſelfe, of this accuſer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> acknowledging how
<pb facs="tcp:13233:22"/> the Pope diſpenſed (as he termeth his declaration) That the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes in <hi>England,</hi> might profeſſe a large obedience: (his owne words) notwithſtanding the excommunication of the Queene.</p>
               <p>But where he addeth this reſtraint; <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> and that it was recalled by <hi>Xistus</hi> the fift, in the yeare 1588. when the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards pretended inuaſion. I anſwer in the firſt caſe: That Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Allane,</hi> better acquainted in theſe affaires, than any proteſtant Writer, ſo long after in <hi>England,</hi> relateth the Popes declaration, for<note place="margin">Cardin. All. ad perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cut. Angl.</note> Catholikes obedience to Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> without any reſtraint or limitation: neither doth this man diſcouer where hee findeth ſuch reſtricting clauſe. And as for Pope <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtus Reuocation,</hi> if any ſuch was, (which he rather imagineth, then prooueth) it is not in force in any opinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not being publiſhed.</p>
               <p>The caſe of the Earle of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> whatſoeuer it was, is not now imputed againſt him, as his libertie and fauour in <hi>England,</hi> ſince then be witneſſe. Therefore it might better be ſuppreſſed, than vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by this diſcouerer.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I haue anſwered to all the obiections of this diſputer, againſt Catholike religion, ſhewing the innocency thereof in the offences obiected, and that Proteſtants be guilty in all, and euery of the pretended crimes. And in that order, I haue made returne of euery Argument, vpon the diſcouerer, and his owne profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But ſeeing his confuſion and rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tition of the ſame, or eq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolent reaſons, was ſuch, as (I haue noted before) that I could not giue him ſo ample allowance in that kinde, as his curteſie deſerued, except I would fall into the like repeating error, I haue reſerued ſome paiment to this place. Before performance whereof, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire my Reader to remember the ſubſtance of his maior propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in all his ſyllogiſmes, that the leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and minors with their conſequence, may be better conſidered. Then thus he writeth: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2. ſupr.</label> Whoſoeuer profeſſe any ciuill power ſoueraigne ouer Kings, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, or indirectly, deny neceſſary right of election, or of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of Princes, &amp; e. ſhall manacle the hands of ſubiects, detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> all obedienee, ſuggeſt a doctrine of forcible depoſing Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> from their thrones, intend, deſigne, or practiſe the murther of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Princes, iuſtifie acts of treaſons, and parricides. And ſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes that doe naturally ſting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo ſoone as they get warmth, are ſed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ious, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> may be challenged and condemned for diſordered and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious
<pb facs="tcp:13233:23"/> are manifeſtly rebellious, deſperate traitors, &amp; not to be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored in the boſome of the Common-wealth. This is the general <hi>Maior</hi> propoſition in all his eight recited Arguments, being one and the ſame (for the moſt part) in ſubſtance and effect; but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied and repeated ſo often, with this mans protracted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice Therefore, ioyning all theſe together in one, for my firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, granted by my aduerſary for moſt certaine, I make this my ſecond generall propoſition. But the Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgy Proteſtant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and patrons, in all times and places, as opportunitie hath beene miniſtred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were in this caſe deſcribed: which, (beſides my former probations) thus I demonſtrate from their moſt dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<note place="margin">Proteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>any.</note> principle, and publike profeſſors, poſitions, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Martin Luther</hi> the firſt knowne Proteſtant, was accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo dogmaticall, principle, and publike, both for doctrine, and practiſe that the prime Proteſtants of that time, <hi>Amſdorſius, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>heſius, Michael, Neander,</hi> and others, honoured him<note place="margin">Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>orf praefat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Caroloſt. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dr. Muſc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raeſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>germ d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abol. Luther. to. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nt. germ fol. 522. 79 to. 3. fo. 334. to. 4. to. 5. fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>98 Colloq. menſal. fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 488 l. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Henrie 8. in Pſa. 71 &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. fol 533. 326. 360. Colloq. menſal. fol 342 343. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>up. edict. Imp.</note> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſe preeminent titles, an other Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> the third and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ias,</hi> the laſt tiumpet of God, an Angel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God, a great Prophet, mightie in word and worke, a man according to the heart of God, the mouth of Chriſt, a God of Diuines, the only Diuine of Diuines, ſupreame Father of the Church, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And himſelfe giueth himſelfe no inferior ſtile; a faithfull Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, an Apoſtle, Euangeliſt, a liuing Saint, receiuing his Goſpel from God, <hi>Iſaias,</hi> &amp;c. ſuch a Maiſter aboue all Doctors, Popes, and Councells, may be termed a publike man, and his poſitions publike. Then he ſaith, that he careth not for Kings: and ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he is in this caſe, that he cenſured king <hi>Henry</hi> the eight of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenburge</hi> the Princes of the imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all orders, the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> the Duke of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unſwicke,</hi> to be vnworthy, eyther of obedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce from ſubiects, or life in themſelues. And giuing the ſame doome of his owne naturall Soueraigne, <hi>George,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxonie</hi> nameth him the calamitie of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, a Tyrant paſſing all Tyrants, <hi>Pilat, Herod, Iudas:</hi> So he ſcorned<note place="margin">To. 6. germ fol. 6. Georg. Wicell. de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retect. Luth. Luther. epiſt ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. inſt. germ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. poteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecul. li. cont. 2. Edict, Imper.</note> the Emperour, and wrote directly againſt his Edicts: hee taught, that Proteſtants hands muſt be imbrued with blood, teaching that he had warrant from God to battaile againſt Princes: Hee telleth vs, it is the nature of the Goſpel, to raiſe warres and ſeditions; that
<pb facs="tcp:13233:23"/> among chriſtians, there is no magiſtrate, no ſuperior: that it is to be intreated by many prayers (ſo holy a thing is rebellion in his ſight, that it muſt be bought with prayers) that the countrymen obey not their Princes: no law, or fillable of law can be impoſed vpon chriſtians, more then themſelues will, neither by men nor Angells: there is no hope of remedy, except all humane lawes be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Munſter</hi> was of the ſame opinion and practiſe, and called rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion<note place="margin">Cacl in act. Luth. Ann. 1525.</note> for his religion, the warre of God; affirming, that hee had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued eſpeciall commaundement from God, to warre againſt Kings, and had promiſe of victorie from heauen. And thereupon ſuch rebellions enſued, that of his owne adherents and traiterous proteſtants, were ſlaine within the ſpace of three mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ths, one hundred and thirty thouſands. The rebellions, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and deſtructions which they performed and publikely pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, by words and Armes, cannot be recounted. And not onely<note place="margin">Luther. l. captiuit Babyl l. de bell. cont. Turc. Munſter in chro. pantal. chronol. fol. 121 &amp;c.</note> theſe miſeries by their owne rebellions, but by Luthers doctrine; that Chriſtians might not fight againſt the Turke; in ſhort time, <hi>Belgrade</hi> &amp; <hi>Rhodes</hi> were taken, <hi>Hungary</hi> was entered, King <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> ſlaine, <hi>Buda</hi> conquered, &amp; <hi>Verima Auſtrae</hi> beſieged with two hundred &amp; fifty thouſand Turkiſh ſouldiers. And the Proteſtants of that Nation, were not content with theſe publike opinions and practiſes of rebellion in themſelues againſt their Emperours <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinande</hi> and <hi>Charles,</hi> whom they perſecuted and beſieged, but conſpired with the Turke himſelfe, both againſt them, and the whole chriſtian world. And their ſucceſſours in <hi>Hungary,</hi> theſe laſt yeares, no better behaued themſelues: theſe directly admitted the Turks entry: the firſt endeuoured to performe it, as their owne<note place="margin">Caſpaectalio hiſt. Symp. ad Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. Defenſ. Stap. contr. Illerich. &amp; Sleid, petr. Frar. ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cont. Sectar. Sleidan. l. 22.</note> letters of conſpiracy, and the comming of the Baſſa of <hi>Buda,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ferdinando</hi> into <hi>Pannonia,</hi> were witneſſes. And <hi>Sleydan</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, a German Proteſtant giueth teſtimony; that this was the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of their diuines of <hi>Magdenburge</hi> publikely teaching in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch rebellions, that ſuch wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res were lawfull.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Sweueland,</hi> the proteſtants themſelues giue alſo teſtimony;<note place="margin">Sweueland. Chit. chron. an. 1593 1594.</note> that the Catholike King thereof, was inforced by his rebellious goſpellers, to make himſelfe a ſubiect vnto their deſignements, and condiſcend, that no Catholike ſhould beare office in that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and catholike ſeruice for the King ſhould be confined only
<pb facs="tcp:13233:24"/> to his owne Chappell. And what rebellions did the Proteſtant<note place="margin">Petr. Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. orat. contr. ſect.</note> Nobillitie, by aduiſe of their Cleargie, raiſe againſt their Prince for this cauſe in former times? And who is ignorant of their ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſeditions and rebellions?</p>
               <p>In <hi>Denmarke,</hi> the ſame dogmaticall opinions were both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely defended and put in execution: What inſurrections and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions<note place="margin">Petr. Frar. ſup.</note> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Proteſtants of that kingdome maintaine by this title? Did they not aſſault the King vnder yeares, and in minority with open warres? Did they not confederate and colleague them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the profeſſed enemies of the kingdome, ſell the Cities to ſtrangers, challenge regall power to their rebellions, and ſuch like intollerable treaſons?</p>
               <p>Let vs come to <hi>Heluetia,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>Geneua,</hi> the mother Church of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eformed, Maiſter <hi>Caluine,</hi> the ſupreame head of the Conſiſtory there, hath told vs before; that Princes (not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Bez. l. iur magiſt. in ſupqit. Sutclif anſw. l. to ſuphl.</note> with him in religion) are rather to be ſpitted vpon, than obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re not worthy to be numbred among men, they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued of all authority. <hi>Beza,</hi> his ſucceſſour in place, ſuccceded him alſo both in opinion and practiſe, arming ſubiects againſt their Prince. And as Maiſter Doctor <hi>Sutliffe</hi> ſaith in effect, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing all authority of Chriſtian Kings and Magiſtrates, and giuing power to ſubiects, not onely to take Armes, but to depoſe and kill the Prince, if he impugne their religion. And accordingly in practiſe, the Proteſtants there, (as <hi>Caluine</hi> himſelfe, Doctor <hi>Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin Sutel. ſup. kiru. pret. diſcipl.</note> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> be witneſſes) depoſed their Soueraigne from his temporall right, and euer ſince, continue in that ſtate of rebellion. And not content with rebellion to one and their owne Lord and Ruler, they celebrated a Councell, wherein it was concluded; that King <hi>Francis</hi> the ſecond, then king<note place="margin">Petr. Fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. orat. contr. ſectar. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſ. Reg. &amp; relig.</note> of <hi>France,</hi> his wife, the Queene, his children, Queene mother, the Nobility, and all good Magiſtrates of that kingdome, ſhould by a certaine day, by treacherous deceits, be put to death.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Burgundy,</hi> a like Aſſembly and Conuenticle was called, kept, and therein decreed at <hi>Cabillon;</hi> that three wormes muſt be taken forth of the world: (theſe men were not content to make their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and practiſe, to one, or a few kingdomes) firſt, the Church of Rome: ſecondly, the noble families of antient houſes: and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all ciuill pollicy, gouernment, and iuriſdiction. How faithfully
<pb facs="tcp:13233:24"/> the Proteſtant Netherlanders, laboured by all ſeditions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, ſo many yeares, and ſtill perſeuer to haue the canon of this holy Councell obſerued; it is too lamentable to be repeated, that ſubiects ſhould maintaine it, or any Chriſtians ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud it.</p>
               <p>Let vs come to <hi>France.</hi> Were not <hi>Caluine, Beza, Othomanus, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Claud. de ſanct. de Saccad. eglif. fol 58. 55.</note> and ſuch publike and dogmaticall Proteſtants, the eggers and inſtruments of all thoſe ſlaughters, rebellions, and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in that Monarchie, wherein they tooke all law, authoritie, and<note place="margin">Petr. Frar. ſup.</note> execution thereof, from the King and Magiſtrates. They conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in one night, to rob all the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ches in <hi>France:</hi> how did they depoſe Magiſtrates, fell Cities, giue the ſpoiles to ſtrangers, &amp;c. what murthering of prieſts and religious men, hanging, cutting, bowelling, rending, ſtrangling, fleaing, drowning, ſtabbing, ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting through with gunnes and arrowes, of religious Prieſts, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring chaines of their eares cut off, about their neckes? how many were buried aliue, and little infants themſelues cut in ſunder, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing men to eate their vndecent parts, cut off, and roſted; and opening the bellies when they liued, to ſee whether they digeſted them, or no; I ceaſe to recount the vnſpeakeable tyranny of thoſe Proteſtant traytors, whom no conditions, peace, or graunt, could ſatisfie.</p>
               <p>After the remembred conſpiracy againſt King <hi>Francis,</hi> his<note place="margin">Genebr. chron. ann. 1560.</note> Mother, wife, children, Nobles, and Magiſtrates at <hi>Geneua,</hi> in the yeare 1560. within two yeares after 1562. they raiſed ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions and ciuill warres againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, that as <hi>Genebrande</hi> writeth, <hi>France</hi> was more endammaged by one yeares ciuill warres, than in all warres paſt by ſtrangers. The King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and Duke <hi>Nyuers,</hi> with others, were ſlaine; the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> treacherouſly murthered, by <hi>Pultrotus Canickname</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> for that fact ſuborned by <hi>Beza,</hi> and the Proteſtant Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and they enforced the Kings to grant them peace and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but they kept neither: for in the yeare 1567. they made a new rebellion, and being ſubdued, accept againe of peace, but<note place="margin">Genebr. chron. 1567. Geneb. chro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in theſe ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es.</note> breake it againe: for in the yeare 1569. they rebell: and in the next yeare 1570. and yet in the yeare 1575. breake againe into rebellion. And ſuch were the miſerable murthers and cala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ies which they brought to that diſtreſſed kingdome, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13233:25"/> firſt ciuill warres and rebellions, aboue 100000. were ſlaine, as <hi>Gaſpar Coligne,</hi> a principall Captaine in thoſe rebellions, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed in an oration before the King. And when <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth forbade by Edict, that no ſuch Proteſtant ſhould publikely<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtor F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucaſe Popelim. li. 27. ſtat Relig. in gal. Sub. Carol. 9. lib. 3 pag. 347.</note> preach, thirteene thouſands of them armed, aſſembled at ſuch a ſermon, in the ſuburbes of <hi>Paris</hi> it ſelfe, and their rebellious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and diſobedience, did not onely extend to their liuing Kings, but indured againſt the dead: as they moſt rebelliouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted King <hi>Francis</hi> when he liued, ſo being dead, they burnt his heart in rebellious de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pight. So they dealt with King <hi>Lewis</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuenth, defaced his Image, diſmembring euery part thereof, and burned his body.</p>
               <p>Concerning this vnited Kingdome of Britaine, I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before ſufficientlie, for the confuſion of all Proteſtants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for euer. I will adde ſomething, and firſt for Scotland. Was not their Goſpell there planted by force and violence to Princes, and by the publique Dogmaticall decrees of <hi>Caluin,</hi> and <hi>Knoxe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Knox hiſt of the church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land pag. 143. 144. Holinſ. hiſt. Scot. anno 1546. Knox ſup. pa. 217 218. 256 258. Holinſh. ſup. ann. 1559. Knox pag. 265. 268. 269. Holinſh. ſup. Knox ſup. pag. 501. 502. 503. &amp; vſque pag 531. Holinſh. ſupr. an. 1566. Dang. poſ. l. 1. c. 6.</note> Apoſtles, and their conſpiracies and practiſe? I referre the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to <hi>Knoxe</hi> himſelfe, to know what publique ſubſcriptions and conſpiracies to this ende, what authoritatiue Sermons to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and Monaſteries, what pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtations of violences againſt the Queenes Edict, and Parliament, what contempt of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, they vſed, in commaunding the Nobles vnder penaltie of excommunication to aſsiſt them, the Biſhoppes and Cleargie, not to reſiſt them, writing, and ſending to all their Sect, to ioyne in Rebellion with them; no Lawe or commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Prince obeyed. They tooke vppon them the Regality it ſelfe, they coyned money by their Authoritie, ſeazed the Inns and renounced all obedience vnto their Princes, terming her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient ſubiects and partakers, a Faction, and threatned them with puniſhment for Treaſon. How wickedly did they reiect hir Authority in Parliament, and made themſelues Supreame, both in Eccleſiaſticall and Temporall buſineſſe? Did they not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Kings and Queenes Secretarie in their ſight, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſame to the Queene her ſelfe, then great with childe with our preſent Soueraigne, ſo to haue brought all into their owne handes, the Iſſue and Poſteritie Regall taken away? And when that holy laſt recited Queene, Mother to his Maieſtie was firſt
<pb facs="tcp:13233:25"/> impriſoned, then expelled her Kingdome by theſe Rebelles, and eſcaped murthering, her Husband being ſlaine by their villanies. How did they condemne all decrees of the State, depoſed the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops as Antichriſtian by their ſupremacie? What comminatory letters did they write to his Maieſtie which now Raigneth, then young in yeares, and the Nobles of that Land to effect their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignements? did not they wholy diſclaime from the Kinges Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and not that only, but made him their ſubiect in preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing lawes vnto him? did not they ſurpriſe and impriſon him as<note place="margin">Declarat. B 1. 2. 3. 4 parliament. Sect. ann. 1584.</note> their Vaſſall? what Traiterous and more than Rebellious excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications and cenſures did they impoſe vppon him? how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">Declarat. 1582. parlia. 1584. c. 7.</note> Conſpiracies did they contriue, how did they force him at Striueling, beſiedged him, tooke the Caſtle, impriſoned the King with violence, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>till he had ſigned their high willes and pleaſures.</p>
               <p>For England I haue ſpoken alreadie more then I deſired, had not ſuch wicked accuſations againſt vs vrged me to breach of ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. And now I will only ſay, that the publique and Dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall poſitions and practiſes of Rebellions by the greateſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſubiects of this Kingdome, the Dukes of Northumberland and Suffolke, (againe and againe) ſo many Nobles to be paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed with obliuion, all their whole Cleagie, Archbiſhoppe, Biſhops and others, not only againſt the law of God and their Queene, but oaths of fidelitie to K. <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, that I am bold to affirme, no Proteſtant obi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctor can giue inſtaunces in any time or Nation of Catholique Regiment or Subiects, where ſo great and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde outrages haue been committed. And yet that which Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes loſt by the new proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dings, ſo many thouſands of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, Religious howſes, Churches, their Religion, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Praiers and Sacrifice for their ſoules ſakes and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, Corrodies, Penſions, and Education for their children, was a greater loſſe to them and their prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion, then euer Proteſtants with their new Faith will beſtow, recompence, or equiualent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite vppon the world.</p>
               <p>Now let vs reuiew this Diſciferers examples of practiſe agenſt <hi>Henrie</hi> the third of Fraunce, the reſiſtment of this preſent King of that countrie, the Bull of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> againſt Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, Henrie</hi> the fourth Emperour excommunicate, <hi>Leo</hi> the third, <hi>Fredericke</hi> the firſt, <hi>Otho</hi> the fift, and King <hi>Childericke. Henry</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:13233:26"/> ſecond in like caſe, which be theſe practicall obiections hee can finde woorthy of reciting againſt vs, ſince the firſt conuerſion of Kings and Countries to Chriſt. Among all which tragedies, let him ſingle forth what kingdome, country, territory, or towne, the Pope poſſeſſeth, detaineth, or keepeth againſt any of thoſe, or any other chriſtian Prince. And compare them with the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants proceedings with Princes, in this ſhort time of their new Goſpel, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir vſurped miniſteriall and popular outrages, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmunications, depoſings, and violence to Princes, doe farre exceede, both for number, and extreameſt iniuries. And ſo many Countries, States, Townes, and territories, both violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken, and ſtill kept from the true poſſeſſors, and reſerued to themſelues, as Princes; doth not onely argue the impietie of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries paſt, and a continued ſtate of rebellion, but giueth demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of their continued opinions, to practiſe the ſame general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all times and places, as occaſions ſhall giue them power and aduantage. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Proteſtants, (and not Catholikes) by this mans arguments, be ſeditious, tray terous, rebellious, intollerable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ninth Reaſon confuted, and returned.</hi> CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>THus he frameth his next Reaſon; <hi>Whoſoeuer doth perfidiouſly either denie, or violate with men of diuerſe religion, an oath, &amp;c. muſt neceſſarily be eſteemed of them, a perſon perfidious and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is his <hi>Maior</hi> propoſition, wherein he muſt needes make ſome exceptions of the lawfulneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. of the thing ſworne, or elſe the Proteſtants which ſwore loyalty to Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> in her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers life, might not ſafely take Armes againſt her, to aduance a forged title: and the Proteſtants which had ſworne obedience to the Pope, could not denie their ſubiection; and whatſoeuer wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is ſworne, muſt be performed: as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> death, becauſe their death was ſworne by <hi>Herod</hi> and the Iewes. But if his propoſition be true, Proteſtants be perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and treacherous, by the example of <hi>England</hi> recited, and all the Countries before remembred: where Proteſtants broke their
<pb facs="tcp:13233:26"/> oaths of loyalty with their Princes, kept not oaths of conditions with ſubiects. But he thus obiecteth: <hi>Popiſh Prieſts are guilty of ſuch perfidie.</hi> And in his proſecuting of this aſſertion, he diſputeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt aequiuocation, although the interrogatorie be vniuſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and chargeth vs with theſe words of Cardinall <hi>Tollet; Cum Iudex non vindice petit Iuramentum vel contra Iuſtitiam, licet vti</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tollet. li. 4. Inſt. Sacerd. c. 21. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>aequiuocatione ſecundum mentem ſuam contramentem Iudicis, vt puta quaerenti feciſti ne illud? reſpondeat non feci, intelligendo inter ſe non hoc tempore aut vt narrem tibi aut aliquid ſimile.</hi> Let this be the caſe as himſelfe hath alleaged it. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n for <hi>Tollet,</hi> ſometimes a Ieſuite, I cite another Ieſuite, famous among <hi>Caſuiſts Emanuel Sa,</hi> who in his Aphoriſmes, writeth of this matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n theſe words; <hi>Quidam</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sa Aphoriſ. men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacium 4.</note> 
                  <hi>dicunt eum qui non tenetur reſpondere ad intentionem Rogantis, poſſe reſpondere aliquid ſubintelligendo, vt non eſſe, ſcilicet it a vt dicere es te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neatur, velſe non habere, ſcilicet vt ei det, licet alij id non admittunt &amp; fortè potiori ratione.</hi> Whereby it is manifeſt, that all Catholikes doe not allow of aequiuocation, where he is not bound to anſwer the Iudge, or examiner proceeding vniuſtly, and not according to law and equitie: that a man in ſuch caſe, is not bound to anſwer at all, if the queſtion concerneth his life, libertie, or fame, his Maieſty, his honourable Councell: and the Proteſtant Biſhops haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented<note place="margin">Conference 14. Ianuar. 1604.</note> vnto, in the conference with Puritans, whether he may ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocate or no, they doe not mention: but other Proteſtants, as <hi>Cranmer, Luther, Caluin,</hi> and others, haue both taught and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed it as lawfull, and ſo doe all Engliſh Puritans, and moſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, (euen in religious buſineſſe) which all men of learning doe condemne, as I will proue in this chapter.</p>
               <p>For our excuſe in this place and queſtion, Catholikes do gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally agree, that to aequiuocate before a competent Iudge, (ſuch as we allow all Magiſtrates in <hi>England,</hi> in temporal cauſes, in as am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note place="margin">Cap. quacunque act. 22. q. 5. Naurar. c. 12. Numb. 8. D. Thom. 2. 2. q. 89. act. 7. ad 14.</note> manner, as if they were of our religion) keeping the order of law, is a mortall ſinne; ſo the canon law it ſelfe, ſo <hi>Nauarre,</hi> Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> and others teach. And if it be defended by diuers Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, (as Proteſtants alſo) that in caſe of vniuſt and iniurious inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatorie, aequiuocacion may be vſed, I deſire to know againſt what vertue this diſcouerer can diſcouer this to be a ſinne. Firſt, it is not againſt iuſtice; for wee ſuppoſed the interrogatory to be vniuſt, then the iniuſtice is in the Iudge, exceeding his commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:13233:27"/> and offering iniurie to the Reſpondent; and not in him which neither contradicteth any law, or offereth iniuſtice to him, to whom no iuſtice belongeth in that cauſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, agenſt verity and truth it cannot be, for the thing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed or denied, is true in the ſence of the Reſpondent, as we ſtill ſuppoſe, and he is not bound to anſwer in other ſence, as before: yea, to aunſwere in the ſence of the iniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious examiner, rather ſeemeth a breach of law and dutie with him, then an obſeruation thereof. Therefore, ſeeing as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth, <hi>mentiri,</hi> to lie, is <hi>eontra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entemire,</hi> to goe againſt a mans minde and meaning; there is neither lie, vniuſtice, or any ſinne in this caſe; but onely in the ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner, there is vſurp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion againſt the lawe, and iniurie to the examminate: and this doctrine of equiuocation in this ſence, is no late inuention. The Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ipture telleth vs, how <hi>Iacob</hi> told his father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that hee was his firſt begotten Sonne <hi>Eſau,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen cap. 27. Ierem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 38. ver. 26. 27.</note> which was not ſo in the ſence of the Patriarke <hi>Iſaac:</hi> ſuch aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocacion alſo the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> vſed to the people, when fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the aduice of the King, hee told otherwiſe then the truth, in their ſence, one thing for another: ſo the Scriptures affirme in diuers ſences, that Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and was not. Our Sauiour himſelfe ſaid to his Apoſtles, he would not goe vp to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and yet ſecretly he went: he fained to his Diſciples, going to <hi>Emaus,</hi> that he would go further. Concerning, the Popes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſacion in oths, when this diſcouerer can proue abuſe in Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like doctrin, in ſuch caſes he ſhal haue further anſwer: in the mean time, he may vnderſtand that meaner ſuperiors then Popes, may irritate the oaths and vows alſo of their ſubiects. So the father may<note place="margin">Gloſſ. 32. q. 2. Mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er, 31. §. 34. Sa v. princeps §. 3.</note> deale with his childe in diuers caſes, and other ſuperiors of their ſubiects: ſo temporall Princes may doe, and alſo legittimate their children, not legitimate, as many teach: ſo King <hi>Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> the eight both thought and practiſed with his daughters, Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whom he had illegittimate, and after, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the contrary, and made them legittimate by ſtatute.</p>
               <p>Now I plainely anſwere to his propoſition of breaking othes, That all Catholikes of this kingdome, both prieſts and others, doe, and ought, ſincerly to acknowledge his Maieſtie to be as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and really true King of all his kingdomes, and ouer all his ſubiects of what profeſſion or calling ſoeuer, as euer any Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:13233:27"/> King his predeceſſor was either of them iointly vnited or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned, and that aſmuch temporall dutie and obedience belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto him, and in their degrees to his honourable Counſaile and inferior Magiſtrates, concerning the affaires of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; and that among other duties, to denie to ſweare, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late an oath, <hi>iuridicè,</hi> iuſtly, and according to courſe of law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and to equiuocate therin, is a ſinne damnable: and that it is the error of <hi>Wickliffe</hi> and later Proteſtants to be of other minde. But ſeing the internall cogitations of men, only naturally knowne to God, defiling the ſoule, and not offenſiue to externall peace, and gouernment, how wicked ſoeuer they be of their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, belong only to the conſiſtory of God, and <hi>internum forum,</hi> we hope it will not be offenſiue, to entreat that the naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences be not arrained in externall courts, which the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf doth not, nor can doe, eſpeciallie where no crime can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected,<note place="margin">Nauarr c. 18. Num. 29. D. Tho. 2. 2. q. 6. articul. 1. 2. Gaiet. 16. cap. Quando de poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit d. 1. c. ſi omnia q. 1. c. 2. de maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. &amp; obed. cap. 2. de Confeſſ. Conference 14. 1604. pag. 92.</note> where there is no ſuch law ordained, where not ſo much as a ſemi-plea, probation, or any accuſation at all is precedent with the iudge, or knowne to the conueuted: And this is not only conformable to the lawe of nature, conſcience, and canonicall proceedings, euen allowed and practiſed in England, but pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely confirmed by his Maieſty, the Archbiſhoppe of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, the Nobles and Biſhops of this kingdome in the late confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. The words of his Maieſty be, <hi>Nemo cogitur detegere ſuam turpitudinem</hi> in ſuch a caſe, and that fame and ſcandall muſt be looked vnto, with a condemning of the Statiſh proteſtants in that point. The Archbiſhopps words be theſe, <hi>If any article did touch</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>the party anie way, either for life, libertie, or ſcandall, he might refuſe to anſwere,</hi> neither was he vrged therevnto; ſemblable was the conſent of all. And if this Rule was generall, I hope Catholikes be not exempted.</p>
               <p>As concerning interrogatories <hi>de futuris contingentibus,</hi> firſt things hereafter to haue an vncertaine being, conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne not a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent certaine ſtate, ſecondlie the Angeiles themſelues naturallie know them not; thirdly the ſoule of Man is ignorant of them; no creature doth by naturall ſcience vnderſtand them: for all ſuch knowledge is either by the obiect preſent, that is not in this caſe, or by the effect, that is to come, or by the cauſe which is here moſt vncertaine. Therefore, the examine of ſuch things we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te
<pb facs="tcp:13233:28"/> may be left to God, who onely in that ſence, is <hi>Scrutat or cordis,</hi> and comprehendeth al cauſes more excellently then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rwiſe it would be hard to deſcipher, how he himſelfe knoweth ſuch things.</p>
               <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to ſpeake to this obiector, concerning his proteſtants pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in diſſimula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion and aeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ocating; Was not the beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of <hi>Luther</hi> the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>angeliſt, ſo vile in this kinde, that neuer any pill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry-mate ſo beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ued himſelfe, as his owne friends, <hi>Fox, Sleiden,</hi> and oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Proteſtants giue demonſtration, and not only in<note place="margin">Fox 2. in Luth. Sleidan lib. 1. Staphil apolog Cocl. in act Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> ciui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l but d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uine matters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all iudgement, no aequiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be allowed: yet at his pleaſure now, he appealed to Pope, now d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d it now recanted his errors, preſently defended them, now ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tted him ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to Cardinall <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>etan,</hi> now refuſed it, now teach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng one now another religion, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beſt ſerued his purpoſe: all hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> owne w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itings be ſtill witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes againſt him. So did the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>England</hi> diſſemble, flatter, change, and rechange, both their faith, and their faſhions, to pleaſe King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, the protector<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, and Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories and ſtatutes are teſtimony to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir confuſion. The like (and worſe) cogging, lying aequiuocating, and diſſembling was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Calum,</hi> as the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Beza,</hi> and<note place="margin">Suru. pret diſeipl. Beza <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u. Staphil Apolog.</note> others beare r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cord: for which, he was baniſhed <hi>Geneua,</hi> for a lying and diſſembling ſeducer; and by ſuch trades, deluded the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zens there, the ſecond ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e reſtord himſelf, &amp; obtaind principallity by ſuch meanes. So alſo he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooſened the <hi>Tygurines,</hi> and among his Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iples, <hi>Iura per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ra, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ua fidem (ſcili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um)</hi> was made a dogmatical princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple. In <hi>England, Cramner</hi> the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oteſtant Archbiſhop o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Canterbury</hi> in his time, and the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e man of that profeſſion, cannot be excuſed, <hi>(Fox</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe being Iudge) from c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unterfaiting the hands of 50. conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on<note place="margin">Fox 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nmar.</note> men to giue a lying credit to his falſe cauſe, as Doctor <hi>Weſton</hi> proued againſt him in the publike Schooles of <hi>Oxford;</hi> and in the ſame place, Doctor <hi>Marti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> made demonſtration, how hee had forſworne himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and beene periured in a moſt high degree, twice at the leaſt, ſwearing obedience to the Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi> And moſt certaine it is, that ſo often he had ſworne to the ſupremacie of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, and King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt: and yet, after all this againe, in the daies of Queen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mary,</hi> he ſwore a new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb facs="tcp:13233:28"/> to the Pope. And <hi>Cranmer</hi> himſelfe confeſſed, hee had ſworne ſuch contrary oathes, but excuſed it by aequiuocation, (ſo much condemned by this accuſer) affirming, as his words doe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, that he ſpake one thing, and meant another, which in cauſes of r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligion (ſuch as this) all men condemne for greateſt wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For what authority ſoeuer men haue to examine, God hath alwaies a true right vnto his honour, not to be denied. Such was the proceeding alſo of <hi>Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> the two great Proteſtant profeſſors of diuinity in <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> whom the whole Engliſh Goſpel could not match; and yet contrary to their fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mer profeſſion and doctrine, they taught what the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament would pleaſe to appoint. And I would demand, whether all the Proteſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt Adherents, to the Dukes of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Suffolke,</hi> were not in this caſe of aequiuocation: and is it not both now ordinary to Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itans, who in acknowledging exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally his Maieſties ſupremacy, and ſuppr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing their Presb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>terie, an eſſentiall point of their faith, and note of their Church, doe not as they beleeue in minde. And externally communicate in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eruice and ſacraments with Proteſtants, whom, and whoſe religion they condemne to hell: and the Proteſtants diſſemble l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kewiſe in the Kings ſupremacy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The tenth Reaſon confuted and returned.</hi> CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>THe tenth and laſt Obiection, being no new Reaſon, but an <hi>Epilogus</hi> of the former, that is; <hi>All Romiſh Prieſts, as Prieſts to profeſſe ſome, and other ſome:</hi> All of thoſe ſed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious poſirions, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore confuted and prooued in euery particular, to be vntrue, and needeth no further anſwer, being before euident; that neither all Prieſts, nor any one Prieſt, as a Prieſt doth, or can maintaine any one diſobedient or ſeditious opinion.</p>
               <p>And whatſoeuer this man, more malitiouſly, than truly or wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſaith; That all Prieſts in the Popiſh Seminaries, vow obedience to their ſuperiors: and therefore, that the ſuperiors maintaining
<pb facs="tcp:13233:29"/> ſuch Seditious poſitions, the ſchollers are bound to their do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rine. Theſe aſſertions be moſt falſly obiected, for firſt the ſchollers doe not vowe any obedience to their Superiors; and that obedience which they promiſe, &amp; practiſe, is in obſeruing the collegiall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es and conſtitutions: as in <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> all Schollers, when they be matriculated &amp; ingraffed to the Vniuerſity, do accuſtome; there is neither vow, oth, nor promiſe to obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their doctrin. Secondlie, this cannot be either vowed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> puniſhed, or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: for no Rector of any colledge is ordinarily a Reader of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie in his Colledge. Thirdly, the Caholike Students neither of England or any other Nation are bound to defend their maſters reading, but in matters of faith, and generallie receaued doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And although <hi>Bellarmine</hi> did ſome times read contro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſies in Rome, And Doctor <hi>Gifford</hi> was a profeſſor in Rhemes, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Stapleton</hi> at Louaine, and the Cardinall at Doway, (which be all readers to Engliſh, which he alleageth;) yet not all Engliſh Prieſts, nor the tenth part of them, were Auditors and Schollers to theſe profeſſors: and yet there is not any one ſentence alleaged, from any of them, or any other Catholike, which in true ſence will bring any preiudice to our moſt holy and innocent cauſe, as I haue made demonſtration.</p>
               <p>Thus it abſolutely remaineth proued (moſt gratious Prince) that if the opinion of any Diuines, concerning depoſing Princes, or making warre againſt them by ſubiects, be treaſonable, and not tollerable in a Common-weale, it is in the Proteſtant profeſſion, by many degrees, exceeding any other, both for opinion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe: and that the opinion of Catholikes, is the leaſt dangerous to this, or any State.</p>
               <p>And for this Diſcouerer, if his late recited Arguments, that ſchollers muſt agree with their Maiſters in ſentence, ſhall ſtand good, himſelfe, (with all Miniſters of his profeſsion) being the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of ſo many ſeditions, and rebellions, Pedagogues, his, and their Anceſtors in proteſtancy, muſt alſo with them be guilty in that kinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:29"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>VVHerefore (moſt mercifull Soueraigne) the poore, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and diſtreſſed Catholiques of this kingedome, humbly entreat licence, to propoſe that queſtion to your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, our earthly King; which guiltleſſe and holy <hi>Iob,</hi> in his greateſt<note place="margin">Iob c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> afflictions, ſo confidently in this manner, diſputed with his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or and King in heauen: <hi>Anſwer me, how great iniquities and ſinnes I haue, ſhew vnto me my wickedneſſe and offences: why doe you hide your face, and ſuppoſe mee for your enemie? you ſhew your power againſt a leafe, toſſed with the winde, and doe perſecute dried ſtubble. Non pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; in amaritudinibus moratur oculus meus:</hi> wee haue not (as we hope) ſinned againſt you, and yet our eyes remaine in bitterneſſe of teares, and can behold nothing but matter of mourning and lamentation. Our nature and Nation, cannot turne your gracious aſpect away: for all of this Dominion, and your moſt fauoured be therein, in the ſame caſe with your Suppliants: that ancient faith and religion which wee defend, cannot be cauſe to ſuch offence; for ſo all Catholikes in the world, that be, and euer were, were to be cenſured by their Princes, with ſuch meaſure. To profeſſe that religion in a Proteſtant regiment, cannot breede ſuch variance; for ſo all other Catholike ſubiects, in all proteſtant Countries, were in the ſame caſe.</p>
               <p>And if one and the ſame religion, can (by any not appearing reaſon) be feared by ſome, ſubiect to ſuſpitions at home, which thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> politicke wiſedome may ſuppoſe, no forraigne proteſtant gouernment hath ſo ſufficiently attended and conſidered; we haue in the ſincerity of our ſoules, without all aequiuocation or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſence, purged our ſelues from all jealoſie of thoſe opinions, pretences, or practiſes, which our enemies could diſcouer, worthy to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obiected. In anſwer whereof we haue both made manifeſt proofe, that we doe not otherwiſe eſteeme of the Proteſtants of this nation, then our ſelues, and thoſe of the ſame faith with vs, in all ciuill ſocieties and communications; that we giue the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall dutie, loyalty, and obedience, to our Soueraigne, honour
<pb facs="tcp:13233:30"/> to Nobles, and loue to all; that although we differ in religion, yet we are ſo farre from making Proteſtants odious, and vnworthy of mutuall communications in ciuill affaires, that we defend their dignities, mageſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acy and rule, againſt men of their owne profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. We doe not aſſigne any ſoueraigne mere ciuill power ouer Princes as the Proteſtants in all places haue taught and practiſed, neither any ſpirituall preeminence in any externe Prelate, preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to Princes right. as our oppoſers doe in Presbiteries, and priuate Miniſters; we haue not denied either election, or ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Proteſtant Princes, as our aduerſaries haue done, both to Catholikes and Proteſtants, for their owne aduan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age: our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine denieth no obedience to you, which was euer giuen to any Chriſtian Prince of <hi>England,</hi> from the firſt, vnto the laſt King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth, by whom, and whoſe eldeſt Catholike Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, your Highneſſe is inthroned. We doe not ſuggeſt the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerers obiected forcible depoſition of elected Princes: Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants haue depriued more in this ſhort being of their Goſpel, by their popular mutenies and priuate authoritie, than all Popes in all ages of chriſtian religion, with publike conſent of Princes and people, haue condiſcended vnto. Proteſtants haue taken Armes and raiſed generall rebellions, more often againſt Princes, not to be condemned, than all Popes haue impoſed cenſures, by publike complaint, againſt thoſe which are noted in hiſtories, for extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary impious. If any hath otherwiſe proceeded, no Catholike may defend it: wee doe not, nor may not by our religion, intend, deſigne, or practiſe, iuſtifie, or defend the murther of Princes, or profeſſe rebellions: the diſcipline of the holy Church and generall Councells, (rules in our religion) denie it for lawfull: what priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges proteſtancy claimeth, what it hath taught and practiſed in that point, <hi>Hungary, Tranſiluania, Germanie, Bohemia, Denmarke, Heluetia, Flanders, Sweueland, France, Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en,</hi> your Maieſties king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and your ſelfe haue beene witneſſes, for many yeares. We doe not allow in opinion, or may practiſe in act, aequiuocation, concealed, double or ſecret ſence, in affaires of Common-weale, and iuridicall interrogatories, and profeſſion of religion. They be Proteſtants which defend and practiſe it in ſuch cauſes, not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable in true diuinitie. Our Prieſts, neither vnder that reduplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue formalitie (as Prieſts) nor otherwiſe maintaine by our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:13233:30"/> any poſition or pactiſe ſeditions, or not obedient: if any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men for want of learning, haue ſeemed to ſpeake or thinke, or for want of grace, dealt or practiſed in other ſence, (no reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion made all men Saints) religion did not teach it, and Catholikes generally condemne it.</p>
               <p>Therefore our confidence cannot but continue, that the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promiſes of your higheſt Authority, of Lenitie, of no bloud for Religion, ſhall not be recalled. The demerritt of a fewe, is no generall impediment. The Scriptures inſtruct vs, <hi>anima quae peccauerit ipſa moriatur;</hi> one man muſt not be are the burthen of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſinnes. All Schooles agree, that no man can condignelie meritte firſt grace, to any other, though but one; then the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of one, or fewe, cannot be demeritte, for innocents to be afflicted; great is the difference of the members in a naturall, and ciuill body, in this cauſe, though the firſt doe ſuffer in ſome ſence together, by connexion in nature, yet in the ſecond, the caſe and reaſon is different.</p>
               <p>Remember moſt worthy Prince, not only how grieuous, but how generall the penalties againſt your Catholiques be enacted: And yet new threatnings be made, that new and more ſtraunge (as <hi>nec inter gentes)</hi> ſhall be ordained: The bodies, honours, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, and riches of husbands, to be puniſhed for their wiues religion, and ſoules; to which they are neither husbands, nor ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors. Children to be taken from Parents, Parents to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> education; which Catholike Princes doe not, and in conſcience, cannot offer to the Iewes themſelues, though (in ſome opinion) the ſlaues of Chriſtians. Children, ſeruants, kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and neighbors are to be made hired Eſpialls, to betray their parents, maſters, kinred, friends, in things, as vnlawfull, which the whole Catholique world honoureth for holy, and they ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their ſoules and fempitermtie that they be ſuch, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Artes, Functions of phiſicke &amp;c. which haue not conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion with Religion, are to be put to ſilence in Catholikes. The ſeuere penaltie for not monethlie profeſſing the Proteſtant faith in Churches, (when in all diuinitie the precept of Profeſſion of true and vndoubted faith, <hi>in ſe,</hi> and <hi>ex ſe</hi> bindeth but ſeldome) is to be increaſed: And others of ſuch condition, too many here to be mentioned, and too grieuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and vnnaturall (we hope) in
<pb facs="tcp:13233:31"/> your Princelie opinion, to be concluded by a Kings conſent. Therefore, vnder ſauour for all, I inſtance in one moſt heauie and generall in thoſe of our deceaſed Queene.</p>
               <p>All Prieſts though neuer ſo dutifull or obedient be cenſured for Traitors, equally with the greateſt offendor in ſinne of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when many guiltleſſe ſoules of that ſacred order, would not for thouſands of worlds once conſent to any ſuch, or a farre infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior offence. A thing moſt ſtraunge and beyond all example, that men in reſpect only of their calling, and function, and that function ſo reuerenced by all our forefathers, ſhould without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe be condemned as guilty of ſo a deteſted crime. We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend holy prieſthood to be a ſacrament, which being ordained by God, cannot be changed by man, Pope, Prelate, or humane power but remaineth in al things, ſubſtance, and doctrine, the ſame which in thoſe dayes when it was ſo honorably eſteemed of all your chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian progenitors, &amp; when our mother Church kept her firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity by your Highneſſe iudgement as we are ready to make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And if your Maieſty ſhould decree the like law againſt any degree, or profeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of your other ſubiects; or the king of <hi>France,</hi> (or other Prince in other eſtate of men) ſhould enact by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that all Miniſters in his Dominions made contrarie to the Romane vſe, approued in his Territories) ſhould be Traitors; the pulpits of England would not be ſilent, to reproue it of great abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity. We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ope therefore; that the rare example of one Queene, wil not ouer ballance ſo many your holy and wiſe Progenitors, and all Princes of the world in this point. And if one againſt ſo many hundreds, coulde carrie (againſt ſo manie reaſons) equiuolent motiue of imitation: yet wee truſt, as you doe not inheritte by Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (or King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, or King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight) whoſe next line and life, rather ſuſpended your Title, then gaue you the Diademe of theſe vnited dominions; but by Queene <hi>Margaret,</hi> and Queene <hi>Marie</hi> of Scotland, Catholike p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inces, and King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeauenth, of England, of the ſame Religion, with all their, and your common Aunceſtors; ſo you rather will inheri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te the ſteppes of them, ſo many, and holy, in this path, which left you ſo great a Title, both to heauen and earth, then followe the lone example, of one woman, or the father, and ſon, a child, from whom no ſuch preeminens is, or can be deriued.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13233:31"/>
               <p> It is the honor of our King in Heauen, (moſt mightie Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) for which we continew in combatte: that Religion which the whole Catholique world in all generall Councelles, Popes, Doctors, and learned men, hath euer profeſſed, wherein this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as our Proteſtants acknowledge) one thouſand yeares ſince,<note place="margin">Ioh. Bal. l. de Script. Angl. in Auguſt. monach. Will. Tetraſtyl.</note> was conuerted, all our Chriſtian aunceſtry embraced, and which all Princes (in the ſchoole of Chriſt) of whome your Maieſtie is deſcended, maintained in themſelues, and ſubiects. That which is ſo generall, cannot be ſurrendred by a ſmall number, of one kingdome: It is not in the power of Man to reſigne the honor of God. Proteſtants and Puritans, which haue turnes, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for all occaſions, which communicate in ſpirituall things, with ſo many different in profeſſion, which can ſubſcribe, and ſweare to Parliament articles, and yet renownce them, take oth of Princes ſupreamacy, yet ſpeake, preach, and print againſt it, communicate in Churches, ſeruice and ſacraments with them, which they ſay, be infidells, and that none going to their Churches, can be ſaued, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their faith and religion to ſtand, or be changed, as pleaſeth Princes, which had not any Church, Chappell, Prince, or ſubiect, of their religion, vntill the daies of <hi>Luther;</hi> and now is the ſame no further, then in one time or Country, may without great loſſe to themſelues, damage to others, or new diſhonour to God, change as the winde ſerueth, their ſpirit ſuggeſteth, or appetite deſireth. Such men may eaſily and onely condiſcend, to change their right, and relinquiſh their intereſt: being ſuch as the Apoſtle thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth: Alwaies learning, and neuer attaining to the knowledge<note place="margin">2. Timoth. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> v. 7</note> of truth.</p>
               <p>Yet neuertheleſſe (dread Liege) if it will pleaſe your Maieſty to vouchſafe vs licence to requeſt, and grace to obtaine, that your owne princely ſentence and cenſure may ſtand: that we ought not to depart further from the Roman Church, (our mother Church by your iudgement) than ſhe hath departed from her ſelfe, when ſhee was in her beſt, and flouriſhing ſtate. And that the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was incorrupted in religion, we humbly againe offer triall before your Highneſſe, with equall c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nditions of Schooles, agenſt the moſt ſelected &amp; choſen Proteſtant Biſhops &amp; doctors of your dominions, to proue, or defend any, or euery ſubſtantiall article, which we now profeſſe, to be agreeable vnto (and not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centing)
<pb facs="tcp:13233:32"/> the knowne, publike, Catholike doctrine of that mother Church, in thoſe your mentioned incorrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed daies of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing the disfauour and penalties againſt lay Catholikes, are grounded vpon their Recuſancy, to be preſent at your prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Seruice; wee humbly beſeech, it may be called to memory, how they haue proteſted in ſeuerall ſupplications, one to your Maieſty, before the end of the laſt Parliament; and the other to Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in the ſeuen and twenty yeare of her raigne, to be builded onely vpon feare of offending God. To which, their ſo long and manilold diſgraces, loſſes, impriſonments, and ſufferings, are ſufficient witneſſe; and for further triall thereof, haue offered to repaire to your Proteſtant Churches and Seruice, without further exception, if the learned of your religion can, and doe proue to the learned of their profeſſion, that it may be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without offence to God: which is ſo much in the opinion of all diuines, as any chriſtian ſubiects can offer in this cauſe. In which minde, as I doubt not but they ſtill continue, ſo I am aſſured, that the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> will giue like conſent. This if your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cleargy doe refuſe, or doe not ſatisfie ſo Chriſtian a requeſt, we hope your Maieſty, being wiſe, learned, iudicious, and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, will perceiue, that the ſeuerity of the lawes againſt them, for that cauſe, is not to be put in practiſe. Theſe things in moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, we commend to your higheſt and mercifull conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: And ſo, deſiring of the Almighty, to grant all happineſſe and proſperity to your Maieſty, and poſterity, we conclude in all dutifull ſubiection, with that antient Father: We will faithfully ſerue you in your Pallace, we will accompanie other your ſubiects in the market, wee will ioyne with them in the field againſt your enemies; onely to you we leaue the Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:13233:32"/>
            <head>Fauls eſcaped.</head>
            <p>In the Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſte, or, are. <hi>tam, cum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chap. 1. Rogesr, Rogers.</p>
            <p>Chap. 2. Haereticus, Haereticis. manimenta, munimenta. not aboue foure or fine, not many. the Prophets and Prieſts of Iuda depoſed: vnder the Prophets and Prieſts of Iuda were depoſed. not now, and are not now.</p>
            <p>Chap. 4. Philopatre, Philopater. which, which is.</p>
            <p>Chap. 5. and it was, and that it was. if, it.</p>
            <p>Chap. 6. natum, nutum. violatore, violatorem. approue, reproue.</p>
            <p>Chap. 9. vermia, Auſtrae. vienna, Auſtriae. Canickname, a nickname. 100000, 1000000. Inns, Irons.</p>
            <p>Chap. 10. vindice, iuridieé. mentire, mentiri. naturall conſciences, internall conſciences. a ſemiplea, a ſemiplene. ſtatiſh Proteſtants, Scottiſh Proteſtants. Caluinianum, caluinianam.</p>
            <p>Chap. 11. puniſhed, promiſed.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
